<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rosarie of our Ladie. Otherwise called our Ladies psalter With other godlie exercises mentioned in the preface.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17546</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120319</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855518</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855518</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21013</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07143)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21013)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 574:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rosarie of our Ladie. Otherwise called our Ladies psalter With other godlie exercises mentioned in the preface.</title>
                  <author>De Vos, M., artist.</author>
                  <author>Collaert, Jan, ca. 1540-1628, engraver.</author>
                  <author>Worthington, Thomas, 1549-1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 127, [1] p. : ill. (metal cuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Apud Ioannem Keerbergium,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Antuerpiæ :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M.D.C. [1600]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed: T.VV. p., i.e. Thomas Worthington, priest.</note>
                  <note>The title page is engraved; at foot: Cum gratia et priuilegio.</note>
                  <note>Many of the engraved illustrations are signed: M. de Vos inuent. Ioan Collaert sculp.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Prayer-books and devotions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21013:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21013:1"/>
            <p>The ROSARIE of our Ladie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Otherwiſe called</hi> our Ladies PSALTER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With other godlie exerciſes mentioned in the Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANTVERPIAE, <hi>Apud Ioannem Keerbergium.</hi> ANNO M. D. C.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>the Virgin and Child flanked by adoring angels and saints</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:21013:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21013:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE, Containing diuers Annotations concerning the Roſarie of our Ladie: and the other Exerciſes here folovving: VVith the cauſes of compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and printing the ſame, in this forme; and certaine commodities enſuing hereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR ſo much (benigne Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like reader) as euerie thing is better vnderſtood, by the expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his proper, or vſual name, it is firſt of al to be noted, that the name of ROSARIE (vvhich properly ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the place vvhere roſes doe grovve, or be reſerued) is here vſed for the forme of praier, vvhich the renovvmed religious father S. Dominicke, about the yeare of our Lord 1200 (or as ſome thinke, a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Prieſt called Peter of Amiens in Picardie, aboue an hundred yeares before) inſtituted, of certaine <hi>Pater noſters, Aues</hi> and <hi>Credes,</hi> together vvith certaine principal Myſteries to be meditated, in honour of our bleſſed Ladie, the virgin MARIE, framed by the number of fiue, like to a Roſe, that hath fiue leaues: Whereof it is called the ROSARIE OF OVR LADIE.</p>
            <p>Which name of Roſarie is vſed ſometi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes largely, and ſometimes ſtrictly, Taken largely it containeth fifteene Decades or Tennes (that is to ſay, fifteene times one Pater noſter with tenne Aues) and three Credes; and hath fifteene Myſteries ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied thereunto, that is, to euerie Decade
<pb facs="tcp:21013:3"/> one Myſterie. And the ſame is alſo called OVR LADIES PSALTER, becauſe it hath ſo manie Aues, or ſalutations of our Ladie, as there be Pſalmes in the Pſalter of Dauid, which are an hundred and fiftie. But ſtrictly taken (as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly ment, vvhen one is appointed for penance, or for pardon, or for other like cauſe to ſay a Roſarie) it containeth only fiue Decades, to witt, fiue Pater noſters and fiftie A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, with one Crede. So that in the great Roſarie (or Ladie Pſalter) be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained three particular Roſaries. And theſe three are reſembled to three ſortes of Roſes, white, read, and damaſke. For as theſe three colours doe ſignifie, ioye, payne, and glorie: ſo theſe three Roſaries do containe three ſortes of Myſteries to be meditated, ioyful, ſorowful and glorious.</p>
            <p>This forme of praying, the firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the Roſarie, did ſo accommodate to the vſe of al faithfull perſons, as it might be both a neceſſarie helpe to vnler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned people, and alſo a moſt profitable exerciſe to the moſt lerned in the world: as vvel for the better auoiding of idle, and hurtful diſtractions in the often repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame prayers, as alſo for the more fruitful eleuating of the mind, meditating vpon the chiefeſt Myſteries of our faith, vvhich concerne our Lord and Redemer his coming into this world,
<pb facs="tcp:21013:3"/> and his going our of the ſame, and the happie effects of both.</p>
            <p>For touching his coming into this world (which vvas ſo long and earneſtly deſired and expected) in the firſt Roſarie are to be meditated theſe fiue ioyful Myſteries. Firſt, how the Archangel Gabriel declared to the immaculate virgin MARIE, that ſhe ſhould conceiue and beare the Sonne of God. Secondly, hovv the ſame ſacred Virgin viſited her coſine Elizabeth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Natiuitie of our Lord, with his Circumciſion, and adoration by the Sages. Fourthly, the Purification of the vnſpotted virgin mother, and Preſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lord in the Temple. Fifthly, the finding of our Lord in the ſame Temple, vvhen at the age of twelue yeares, he had bene loſt three dayes. Lykewiſe in the ſecond Roſarie, are to be meditated fiue ſorowful Myſteries pertaining to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours going forth of this world, by his moſt painful Paſſion, and death, which are theſe. Firſt, his great agonie, and penſiue prayer in the garden. Secondly, his cruel whipping, vvith other manie extreme and vile iniuries. Thirdly, his crovvning vvith thornes, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to death. Fourthly, his carying of his ovvne Croſſe. Fifthly, his crucifying, and death thereupon. Finally concerning the effects of his coming into this vvorld, and of his going forth of it againe, in
<pb facs="tcp:21013:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21013:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21013:5"/> the third Roſarie are to be meditated theſe fiue glorious Myſteries. Firſt, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our Lord. Secondly, his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion into heauen. Thirdly, the coming of the Holy Ghoſt. Fourthly, the bleſſed death and Aſſumption of our Soueraigne Ladie in ſoul and bodie. And fiftly, her Coronation and ſingular dignitie, aboue al other Saincts and ſeruants of God.</p>
            <p>Thus much in general is euident by the tradition, and continual practiſe of al Catholike nations, for the ſpace of foure or fiue hundred yeares at leaſt: that is, ſince the time of S. Dominicke, or before. And of the ſame antiquitie and authoritie is the vſe of Beades, which were inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for the better obſeruing of the preſcribed number of prayers, in ſaying the vvhole Roſarie. And conſidering, that no man can vvel meditate vpon anie Myſterie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he both particularly know, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly remember, the ſpecial points therof, vve can nor doubt, but that Chriſtian people vere both taught the particular pointes of al the aboue mentioned fiftene Myſteries, and alſo had ſome forme or order preſcribed, vvherby they might the better remember the ſame pointes, euerie one in his place. Which inſtructions being, not commonly extant, and the vſe of Beads alſo inhibited, and made dangerous to Catholikes, liuing amongſt Heretikes in this age; for remedie of both theſe defects, a certaine Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="tcp:21013:5"/> Prieſt, and priſoner for the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion, in the tovvre of London and there alſo depriued both of bookes and Beades, framed for him ſelf a forme of meditation in ſaying the Roſarie, by noting ſo many particular pointes in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one of the fiftene Myſteries, that ech Myſterie ſeruing his owne decade, euerie <hi>Pater noſter, Aue</hi> and <hi>Crede</hi> ſhould haue their competent and particular pointes alotted. Wherby as wel the iuſt number of prayers, may without beades be exactly obſerued, as alſo ſufficient and apt matter be redely remembred, and the mind more eleuated to God, and idle diſtractions bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter auoided.</p>
            <p>This priuat Exerciſe, albeit very vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect (as not purpoſed for the print, but rudely writre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a priuat freind) yet did ſo content and pleaſe ſome wel diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed perſons, that preſently, without knowlege of the author, they cauſed it to be printed, and ſo made common to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Wherby at laſt it came into the handes of one, that knew better the authors mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. who finding manie faultes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in the edition, thought good to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and a mend the ſame, and adorning it with Images to ſet it forth anew, as wel to ſatisfie the good deſires of ſuch as firſt did print it, as alſo for the like profite to others, who either had it not, or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not the vſe therof before.</p>
            <p>And for al their ſakes hath alſo added
<pb facs="tcp:21013:6"/> hereunto, the Corone of the ſame moſt facred virgin, firſt inſtituted by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid religious father S. Dominike, or by ſome of his folovvers, and lately reduced into the like forme, by the ſame author, and novv firſt printed vvith the like pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. For the better vnderſtanding of the name, vſe, and fruite vvherof, it is to be noted, that it is called the CORONE, or Crowne of our Ladie, becauſe it contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſo manie AVES, or ſalutations of the B. Virgin, as ſhe is ſuppoſed to haue liued yeares in this vvorld, before ſhe receiued her Crovvne in heauen, vvhich are three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and three. And it is diuided into ſeuen partes, Euerie part containing one <hi>Pater noſter</hi> and tenne <hi>Aues,</hi> ſauing the laſt, which hath one <hi>Pater noſter</hi> and only three <hi>Aues,</hi> with a <hi>Crede</hi> in the end. In ſaying of vvhich Corone, certaine parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular points of the ſingular priuileges, vertues, and dignities of the ſame B. vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, grounded vpon the teſtimonie of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he Scriptures, and auncient Fathers, are ſo accommodated to euerie <hi>Pater noſter, Aue,</hi> and <hi>Crede,</hi> in hiſtorical order, from before her Conception vnto her moſt glorious Coronation, that as nere as vvel may be obſerued, in the firſt part are propoſed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe things to be meditated, that belong to the preparation made for her coming, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe was borne. In the ſecond, ſuch as pertaine to her birth and education. In
<pb facs="tcp:21013:6"/> the third, how ſhe cooperated with the B. Trinitie, in Chriſts incarnation and nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite. In the fourth, her participation with him, both in ioyes and afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, moſt part of his life in this world. In the fifth her ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular compaſſion in the time of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and death. In the ſixth, the reſt of her life, with her death and aſſumption. And in the ſeuenth and laſt part, her moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Coronation, and exaltation aboue al Saincts and Angels, next to her ſonne abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue al created perſons.</p>
            <p>And becauſe Chriſts Crowne and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is aboue al, here is added alſo an other godlie exerciſe called the CORONE OF OVR LORD. Which albeit in dignitie is firſt and chiefeſt, yet here it is placed in order of the time in which it was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by a certaine holie Heremite <hi>in monte Camaldulenſi,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1515. alowed and priuileged with indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences by Leo the tenth, and others his ſucceſſors. This Crowne conſiſteth of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and three <hi>Pater noſters</hi> (according to the number of yeares, which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our liued in this world) and foure <hi>Aues</hi> with one <hi>Crede.</hi> And ſo is diuided into foure partes, ech part co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taining tenne <hi>Pater noſters,</hi> and one <hi>Aue,</hi> ſauing the laſt which hath but three <hi>Pater noſters,</hi> and one <hi>Aue,</hi> with the <hi>Crede</hi> in the end. And to
<pb facs="tcp:21013:7"/> theſe prayers are likewiſe applied certaine Articles or points, of our Sauiours acts and ſufferings, to be meditated in this order. In the firſt part, of his coming into this world. In the ſecond, of his conuerſation amongſt men for their ſaluation. In the third, of his going forth of the world, by his bitter Paſſion and death. And in the fourth part, of his moſt glorious victorie and Exaltation.</p>
            <p>Finally here is alſo added an other briefe ROSARIE of fiftene <hi>Pater noſters,</hi> with ſo manie <hi>Aues,</hi> and one <hi>Crede,</hi> in memorie of ſeuen principal ſorowes and eight ioyes of our B. Ladie. Which Roſarie who ſo euer ſaith dayly, ſhal in the ſpace of a yeare, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite ſo manie <hi>Pater noſters,</hi> and <hi>Aues,</hi> as our Sauiour ſuſteyned woundes for vs in one day, as is ſayd to be reueled to S. Brigit.</p>
            <p>And thus much might ſuffice for this Preface, touching the contents, and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of printing this litle booke, but that ſome may perhaps moue a doubt or two againſt this maner of praying, which I thought neceſſarie here to ſolue before I conclude.</p>
            <p>The firſt doubt is, vpon what authoritie or godlie example this numbring of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers is grounded.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwere, That we haue for this, not only the practiſe of the whole Church of later time, that is, of foure or fiue hundred yeares (which is a ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:21013:7"/> warrant to al Catholikes, for that ſo vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal a practiſe of the whole Church, can not be erroneous (as S. Auguſtin Proueth in his expoſition of the. 118. Pſalme. v. 43. and very often againſt the Donatiſts) but alſo the confirmation of holie Scriptures, and examples of Chriſt him ſelf, and of diuers Saincts euen from the primitiue Church to our time. As for example, we read in the 6. chap. of Iſay, and in the 4. of the Apocalyps, that the Angels and other Saincts, ceaſſe not day nor night to repete continually one thing, ſaying: HOLIE, HOLIE, HOLIE Lord God of Hoſtes. Which forme of praiſing God. the Church militant in the ſelf ſame wordes obſerueth in the Canticle TE DBVM, and in the Preface of the daylie Sacrifice. Likewiſe the Royal prophet Dauid offered vp his holie prayers, and praiſes to God ſeuen ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes euery day, as him ſelf teſtifieth in the 118. Pſalme. And the whole Church of Chriſt doth the ſame, in the ſeuen Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical houres. Alſo our B. Sauiour in the garden of Gethſemani, the night before his death repeted the ſame prayer three ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, as the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſts do exactly note. And (in the 18. of S. Luke) he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth, that we continue and perſeuere in prayers. Which the vulerned (eſpecially) can not doe, but by often repeting the ſame pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. S. Barthlemew the Apoſtle, agreably to his Maſters inſtructions, prayed euery day an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred times (as witneſſeth Abdias)
<pb facs="tcp:21013:8"/> The ſame did S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Macha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us in Aegypt, manie yeares together (as Zozomenus recordeth lib. 6. cap. 29) And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul the Heremit recited euerie day three hundred prayers (as is written in his life). For obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of which number, he put ſo many litle ſtones in his boſome and taking them forth one by one after euerie prayer, when al were ſo remoued, he knew thereby that his taſke of prayers was accompliſhed. Euen as Catholike people doe now by their beades, and may do by obſeruing the particular pointes of the Myſteries, ſet downe in this booke, and that without booke (after ſome diligent practiſe) or by anie other like meanes.</p>
            <p>An other doubt is. How this maner of praying, with meditation, vpon ſuch My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, as are not expreſſed by the wordes of the prayers, may helpe attention, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the fruit of prayer, and not rather hinder the ſame, by leading the mind of purpoſe into other cogitations, different from the proper and literal ſenſe of the wordes? For ſolution hereof it is to be noted, that in vocal prayer there be three ſortes of attention that may be obſerued, and three fruites which may be reaped (as the Angelical Doctor S. Thomas teacheth 2. 2. q. 83. a. 13.) One attention is to pronounce the wordes perfectly, and diſtinctly. An other is to attend to the ſenſe of the ſame wordes, either literal or ſpiritual. The third atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:21013:8"/> is, to remembrer the cauſe why we pray, or the thing we pray for, which ought euer to be the glorie of God, the ſaluation of our owne and other ſoules, or ſome other good thing directed thervnto. And the firſt effect of prayer is, to merite: the ſecond, to obtayne that which is due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly requeſted; and the third is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual refection of the mind. So then I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the doubt propoſed: that to al the three effects it is neceſſarie, that we intend and purpoſe to haue the firſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. but if afterwardes of frailrie the mind be caried away, the fruit of that prayer is not therfore loſt, or fruſtrat, but hath his effect, by vertue of the former intention and purpoſe. And the ſame is to be ſaid of the ſecond attention, if one (that vnderſtandeth the language, in which he prayeth) doth purpoſe to marke the ſenſe of the wordes, and yet afterwards faileth to performe it. But betvvene this ſecond, and the firſt attention this is the difference, that albeit this ſecond is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, yet it is not ſo neceſſarie as the firſt, neither in the beginning nor in the reſt of the prayer. For thoſe that pray in a tongue they vnderſtand not, can not haue this attention, and yet their prayer is profitable, and fruitful, by the vniuerſal iudgement of al Doctors. The third attention, by which the mind is lifted vp to God, and good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual deſires and cogitations, is not
<pb facs="tcp:21013:9"/> only neceſſarie in the beginning (like as the firſt attention is) but alſo moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie of al the three, to be kept ſtil without interruption, in reſpect of the third effect. And this the vulerned may alſo haue, pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing in an vnknowne tongue. And it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo aboundeth, that the mind forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth al other things; as S. Thomas, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him S. Hugo de Victore, and others do teach. And in this caſe it ſupplieth alſo the defects, which often happen in the other two attentions, as wel in thoſe vocal prayers which we are bound vnto, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Church, or other obligation (ſo there be no notable defect in reciting the wordes) as in other prayers, which we are not bound to ſay. And finally this atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion perfecteth, ſo much as can be in this tranſitorie life, the ſpiritual repaſt of the faithful ſoule: which attention ceaſſing, neceſſarily the refection of the mind ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with alſo vaniſheth, but yet the other two effects do not therfore ceaſſe, but remaine ſtil. For not with ſtanding the mind be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, by humane frailtie without volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie conſent, to thinke vpon baſe and terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial things, yet the prayer may both me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite increaſe of grace, and obtayne the things that be aſked. And much leſſe is euery euagation of mind in prayer to be reputed a ſinne, but that only which we either volunrarily admitte or willingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, of ſome vaine or hurtful thing. And ſo you ſee the maner of praying propoſed
<pb facs="tcp:21013:9"/> in this booke doth not hinder due atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the obiection preſuppoſeth, but greatly helpeth the ſame, and bringeth alſo other ſpiritual commodities. Of which ſome may be here briefly noted.</p>
            <p>For firſt, beſides that the mind is hereby directed to the beſt and moſt neceſſarie attention required in prayer, ſuch alſo as be not ſo wel inſtructed already, may by this forme of ſaying the Roſaries and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones here enſuing, learne many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and moſt neceſſary points of Chriſtian doctrine: which being once knovven, can not but moue a true Chriſtian hart to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, more or leſſe, cogitation and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo great and ſingular benefites, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtovved vpon vs by Almightie God. And the more one ſhal meditate vpon the ſame, the more alſo ſhal his knovvlege be ſtil increaſed. So knovvlege and meditation do mutually helpe and increaſe ech other, but one vvithout the other auaileth little. For as meditation vvithout knovvlege is erroneous: ſo knovvlege vvithout medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is drie and fruitles. But both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvil eaſely inkindle the ſoul vvith the loue of God, and feede it with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titual refection, and ſturre vp and inflame the deſire to al poſſible endeuour for the increaſe of Gods glorie, and health of their ovvne and other mens ſoules. Likevviſe out of this varietie, and copie of diuine Myſteries and benefites, the vvel diſpoſed may at al times and occaſions, chooſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb facs="tcp:21013:10"/> and fit pointes to meditate vpon in al their prayers vocal or mental. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, by diligent vewing and beholding the pictures here placed, euerie one may better conceiue and conſider the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by them repreſented, and be perhaps more moued to deuotion by ſight therof, then by only reading. If any therfore wil vſe this exerciſe, no doubt but for revvard of their paines, they ſhal reape hereby no ſmal fruite and increaſe of pietie. You at leaſt (my deerely beloued in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt) vvho haue not better meanes to further your deuotions vvithal, vſe this helpe. And vouchſafe of your charitie to commend al vs, (vvho to do you good haue beſtovved labour and coſt, in ſetting forth this little vvorke) amongſt your other deere frendes, vnto our B. Lord, and to his B. mother our Ladie, to our propre Angels, and ſpecial Patrons, and the vvhole Court of heauen, in your ſvveete deuotions. Amen. 25. of March. 1590.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ovvne al and euer in Chriſt, T. VV. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Psalter">
            <div type="rosary">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21013:10"/>
               <head>THE FIRST ROSARIE OF OVR LADIES PSALTER; reſembled to a white Roſe, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fiue ioyful Myſteries.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In nomine Patris &amp; Filij <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> &amp; Spiritus Sancti.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>cross encircled by five roses</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat ſoeuer thou doeſt (ô my ſoul) in word or in worke, do al in the name of our Lord IESVS CHRIST, and to the glorie of God. For God forbid I ſhould glorie, ſauing in the CROSSE of our Lord IESVS CHRIST.</p>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21013:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>1. <hi>Mysterium gaudioſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>the annunciation and incarnation</figDesc>
                        <head>1. PATER NOSTER</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21013:11"/>
                  <head>The Annunciation, and Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>THe moſt Bleſſed Trinitie, one God Almightie, moſt iuſt &amp; moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, forſeeing al makind fallen from moſt happie eſtate (wherin he was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated) into infinite miſerie and calamitie; As to haue loſt original iuſtice, grace, vertues, and moſt excellent gifts, and qualities, by tranſgreſſing Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: And contrariwiſe to haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred, ſinne, death, and eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And that he could not be reſtored to his former eſtate, by the worke or vertue, of anie man, or Angel, or anie other pure creature: of his infinite loue (which is moſt agreable to his Diuine goodnes) decreed defore al worldes, that the Sonne of God (the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſame moſt Holie Trinitie) ſhould take mans nature, and being made man ſhould pay our ranſome by his death on the Croſſe. And ſo not only in general take away the ſinne of the world, but alſo in particular iuſtifie, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie, and bring al thoſe, to whom this moſt ſouereigne meanes is rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, to euerlaſting life, for which we were firſt created.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21013:12"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our merciful Lord promiſed this ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIATOR, immediatly after the fal of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaying: that the ſeede of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould cruſſe in peeces, the ſerpentes head.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our heauenlie Father renewed the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me promiſe to the holie Patriarch Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, ſaying: In thy ſeede al nations ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be bleſſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Almightie God eftſones iterated the ſame promiſe, to king Dauid ſaying: of the fruit of thy Ioynes, I wil ſet vpon thy ſeat. And eſtabliſh his kingdom for euermore.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>About 4000. yeares from the creation of the world, the Archangel Gabriel being ſent from God, to the moſt pure virgin Marie, ſaluteth her: HAYLE FVL OF GRACE, OVR LORD IS WITH THEE; BLESSED ART THOV AMONG VVOMEN.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The moſt humble virgin is trubled with this ſpeach, thinking with her ſelf, what maner of ſalutation this may be! <hi>For ſhe expected nothing leſſe, then to heare herſelfe ſo highly praiſed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21013:12"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Feare not MARIE, ſayeth the Angel: for thou haſt found grace with God. Behold thou ſhalt conceiue, and beare a Sonne, and ſhalt cal his name IESVS,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She inquiereth: How (or by what meanes) ſhal this be donne, for I know not man? <hi>Hauing before this vovved perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual virginitie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Angel anſwereth: the Holie Ghoſt ſhal come vpon thee, and the powre of the Hiegheſt ſhal ouerſhadowe thee. Therfore, that which of thee ſhalbe bor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne Holie ſhalbe called the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Behold Elizabeth thy coſin, ſhe alſo hath conceiued a ſonne, in her old age, and this moneth is the fixt to her that is called barren. For there ſhal not be anie thing impoſſible with God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The holie virgin anſwereth: Behold the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmaide of our Lord, be it done to me according to thy word. And imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly THE WORD IS MADE FLESH, and dwelleth with vs; God and man in one Diuine Perſon.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21013:13"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>2. <hi>Mysterium gaudioſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Mary visits St. Elizabeth</figDesc>
                        <head>2. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21013:13"/>
                  <head>Our bleſsed Ladie viſiteth S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE moſt humble virgin, vvho euen now, receiued an Ambaſſage from heauen, by an Archangel ſent from God: who by the ſame Archangel is denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ful of grace: vvho hath novv concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in her virginal vvombe, the Onlie Sonne of God, Chriſt our Lord, Redemer of the vvorld: vvho is novv made the mother of God, and Queene of al creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: by hovv much ſhe is higher exalted, ſo much the more lovvly ſhe be haueth her ſelfe; iudging it a dutifull office for her ſelfe, the younger, to viſite her aged Coſin Elizabeth, novv ſix moneths gone vvith childe. Wherupon, neither preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her ovvne preeminent dignitie, nor diſdayning the meane eſtate of her coſin, nor terrified vvith the length or ſharpnes of the iourney, nor hindred vvith vvhat other impediment ſoeuer, vvhich might ſtay her in this purpoſe, addreſſing her ſelfe to trauel al on foote, goeth vvith ſpeede into the hil-countrie, into a citie of Iuda, called Hebron. Admire therefore (my ſoul) as vvel the humilitie as magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie of the virgin, mother of God. Who thought no office to baſe nor hard, for her to vndertake that perteyneth to pietie.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21013:14"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The bleſſed virgin coming to the citie, goeth into Zacharies houſe, ſaluteth her coſin Elizabeth, congratulating her conception of a Sonne, by Gods ſpecial fauour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>As Elizabeth heareth the ſalutation of the ſacred virgin, the infant leapeth in her wombe for ioy. And is withal ſanctified in his mothers wombe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And Elizabeth repleniſhed alſo with the Holie Ghoſt, crieth out with a loud voice, ſaying: BLESSED ART THOV AMONG WOMEN, AND BLESSED IS THE FRVIT OF THY WOMBE.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering the worthines of the humble virgin, and her owne meanes, admiring ſaith: Whence is this to me, that the Mother of my Lord doth come vnto me!</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The virgin mother prophecieth, and praiſeth God with a Canticle, ſaying: MY SOVL DOTH MAGNIFIE OVR LORD. AND MY SPIRIT HATH REIOICED, IN GOD MY SAVIOVR.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21013:14"/>
                     <head>Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Maria.</head>
                     <p>Eliza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eths time being come to be deliuered, ſhe bareth a ſonne, wherof her neighbours and kinſſolke hearing come and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gratulate the ſame with her</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The eight day the childe is circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed, manie deſiring to haue him called Za<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>charie, after his father; his mother would haue him called IOHN At laſt his father writeth, IOHN IS HIS NAME.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And forthwith Zacharies mouth is opened <hi>(vvho had bene tenne moneths dumme, becauſe he did not beleeue the Angels vvordes, that his vvife ſhould beare a ſonne)</hi> and he prophecieth, ſaying: BLESSED BE OVR LORD GOD OF ISRAEL.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And al that heare theſe things admire in their hartes, ſaying: What an one, trowe ye, ſhal this childe be! For the hand of our Lord was vvith him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our B. Ladie taking leaue of her coſine, returneth towards Nazareth the next day after the circumciſion of the child. <hi>as it ſeemeth, for the text ſayth; She taried vvith Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth about three monethes. And this day the Church celebrateth the Viſitation of our Ladie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21013:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>3. <hi>Mys terium gaudioſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>the Nativity</figDesc>
                        <head>3. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21013:15"/>
                  <head>The Natiuitate of our Lord.</head>
                  <p>AFter the holie virgin returned to Nazareth, from viſiting her coſin, her huſband Ioſeph perceiuing her to be with child, is much trubled in mind, and doubtful what to do. For on one ſide he feareth the law, if he conceale, that his wiues conceiuing is not by him: On the other ſide, he knoweth the virgin, his ſpouſe, to be of ſo godlie, chaſt, pure, and immaculate life, that he dare not accuſe her, nor bring her into anie (be it neuer ſo ſmal) ſuſpicion. She in the meane time being moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, and moſt modeſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueleth not, no not to her moſt deare huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, this ſo great a Myſterie, wrought in her by the powre of God. In fine Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph being iuſt, and holie, to auoide per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie, determineth ſecretly to leaue her: But while he thus thinketh, behold an Angel of our Lord appeareth to him in ſleepe, ſaying: Ioſeph ſonne of Dauid, Feare not to tarie with Marie thy wife. For that which is conceiued in her, is of the Holie Ghoſt. And ſhe ſhal bring forth a Sonne: And thou ſhalt cal his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me IESVS. For he ſhal ſaue his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their ſinnes.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21013:16"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>By co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of Caeſar Auguſtus, that al ſhould be enrolled, euery one in the place whence they were deſcended: Ioſeph with his ſpouſe goeth to Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a citie of Dauid, becauſe they were of his houſe and familie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>There by reaſon of their pouertie, and great concurſe of people, not finding row me in anie Inne, they take a poore lodging (as they may) in a ſtable.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>In this place our Lord and Sauiour, King of al kings, the Sonne of God is borne, wrapped in clothes, and laid in a manger by an oxe and an aſſe, and is warmed by their breaths.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Forth with an Angel appearing to Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards ſaith to them: Beholde, this day is borne to you a SAVIOVR, which is Chriſt our lord in the citie of Dauid, and you ſhal find him ſwadled in clothes, and laid in a manger.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And ſodenly, there was with the Angel an heauenlie armie, praiſing God, and ſinging: GLORIE IN THE HIGHEST TO GOD: and in earth peace to men of good wil.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21013:16"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Then ſay the ſhepheards: Let vs go to Bethlehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſee this thing which God hath done, and ſhewed to vs. And going with ſpeede, they finde the childe laid in a manger, and ſo returning glorifie God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The eight day the childe is circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed, and his name called IES vs: that is SAVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVR, according as the Angel had before ſignified to the virgin mother, and to Ioſeph his ſuppoſed father.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Three Sages <hi>(Kings or Princes)</hi> knowing by the apparition of a glorious ſtarre, that the king of Iewes (their expected MESSIAS) is borne, come from the Laſt to Ieruſalem, to adore him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>King Herod and al Ieruſalem with him are trubled, hearing theſe newes: yet there the Sages lerne of the hiegh Prieſts, that Chriſt ſho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uld be borne in Bethlehem.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Sages going towards Bethlehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſee the ſtarre againe, and it leadeth them euen to the houſe, where they finde the childe, and adore him; euerie one offering three giftes; Gold, Frankincenſe, and Myrrhe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21013:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>4. <hi>Mysterium gaudioſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>the presentation of Christ at the temple</figDesc>
                        <head>4. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21013:17"/>
                  <head>The Purification of our Ladie, and Preſentation of our Lord.</head>
                  <p>KIng Herod expecteth the returne of the Sages, whom he had willed, to ſeeke diligently for the childe, and when they ſhould finde him, to informe him therof, that he alſo might go and adore the ſame new borne king (for ſo he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, meaning in dede to murder Chriſt in the cradle) but God vvarned the Sages by an Angel in their ſleepe, not to returne to Herod; and ſo they teturne into their countrie by an other vvay. In the meane time, the immaculate virgin (needing no purification, nor being bound to that cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the Lavv, yet vvilling to obſerue the cuſtome of other vvomen) prepareth for her iourney, as alſo to make her obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to, yea and aboue the ſame lavv, a pare of turtles and tvvo pigeons; for albeit a pare of either of both ſortes vvou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d haue ſuffiſed for that purpoſe: yet ſhe offereth of ech ſort a paire: And that not vvithout Myſterie, the turtles being ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie birdes, ſignifiing the ſecret ſighes and cries of the ſeruants of God: and the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons being ſociable, ſignifying the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prayers of the vvhole Church. <hi>Both vvhich ſhe offereth novv in heauen, as Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of al.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21013:18"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The virgin mother goeth vp to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, carying thither her ſonne, with her oblation, Ioſeph her huſband, and ſuppoſed father of IESVS, accompai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and aſſiſting her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The ſacred virgin preſenteth her Sonne to God in the Temple, the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith day after his birth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Simeon, a iuſt and religious old man, had receiued an anſwere of the Holie Ghoſt, that he ſhould not die, til he had firſt ſeene the ANOINTED of our Lord, that is, CHRIST the expected MESSIAS.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>This holie old man Simeon (by the particular prouidence of God) is preſent in the Temple, when the childe IESVS is brought thither by his parents to be preſented.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The venerable old man ſeeing the childe IESVS, taketh him by and by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his armes, and his hart ful of ioy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth in ſpirite.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21013:18"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>So ſoone as he can ſpeake for ioy, he bleſſeth God, ſaying: NOVV THOV DOEST DIMISSE THY SERVANT, O<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> LORD, ACCORDING TO THY VVORDE, IN PEACE. BECAVSE MYNE EYES HAVE SEENE THY SALVATION.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The parents admiring the things that are ſproke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concerning the childe, Simeon bleſſeth them, and ſayth to the mother: Behold this childe is ſet, vnto the ruine, and vnto the Reſurrection, of many in Iſraël.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And he ſayth moreouer to the mother; A ſworde ſhal pearce thyn owne ſoule; <hi>that is, griefe and compaſſion of this thy ſonnes Paſsion, ſhalbe to thee as death it ſelfe, or, as a ſvvorde paſsing through thy hart.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>An auncient religious widowe called Anne, who remayned night and day in the Temple, ſeruing God by faſtings and prayers, doth alſo prophecie of this childe, to al that expect the redemption of Iſrael.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>After they haue done al things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the lawe, they returne homewards in peace and ſafetie, <hi>God not ſuffering Herod to ſuſpect, that this is the childe, vvhom he feareth, and ſeeketh to deſtroy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21013:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>5. <hi>Myſterium gaudioſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Mary finds Jesus at the temple</figDesc>
                        <head>5. PATER NOSTER</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21013:19"/>
                  <head>The finding of our Sauiour, when he had bene three dayes loſt.</head>
                  <p>KIng Herod perceiuing, that he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded by the Sages, is exceeding an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, and ſending a troupe of ſoldiars, murdereth al the men children, that are in Bethlehem, and in al the borders ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; from tvvo yeares old and vnder, To the number of fourteene thovvſand: vvho al, by ſpecial priuilege receiue crovvnes of Martyrdome. In the meane time Ioſeph admoniſhed by an Angel, taking the child and his mother, and parting the ſame night, fleeth into Aepypt: and ſo is fulfilled the prophecie of Eſay: <hi>Our Lord aſcendeth vpon a light cloude</hi> (Chriſt being caried by his mother à virgin) <hi>and ſhal enter into Aegypt: and the Idols of Aegypt ſhalbe ouerthrovvne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his face, and the hart of Aegypt ſhal lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh;</hi> verified by the falling dovvne of Idols, whileſt Chriſt is in Aegypt, <hi>vvhich vvas about the ſpace of ſix yeares.</hi> Then Herod dying, they returne into the land of Iſrael. But hearing that Archelaus reigneth in lurie, for Herod his father, they feare to goe thither; and Ioſeph being ſo vvarned in ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>epe, they repaire into the quarters of Galilee, and dvvel in Nazareth, vvherof our Sauiour is called IESVS of Nazareth.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21013:20"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IESVS being twelue yeares old, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their cuſtome at the ſolemne day of Paſch, he and his parents goe vp vnto Ieruſalem, to keepe there the Feaſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The dayes of the Feaſt being expired, the childe IESVS remaineth in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, his parents returning homewards not knowing of his abode.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>They ſuppoſing him to be in the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panie, goe a dayes iourney without him and at night they ſeeke him among their kinsfolke and acquaintance, but finde him not.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The next day they returne very ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful and lamenting, towards Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem to ſeeke him there.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>After three dayes they finde him in the Temple, ſitting in the middes of the Doctors, hearing them and aſking them queſtions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21013:20"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Al are aſtonied that heare the childe ſpeake, as wel at his wiſdome in deman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, as in his anſweres.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>His mother ſayth to him: Sonne, why haſt thou ſo done to vs! Behold, thy father and I ſorowing did ſeeke thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He ſayth to them: What is it that you ſought me? did you not know that I muſt be about thoſe things which are my fathers affayres?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He then goeth downe with them to Nazareth, and is ſubiect to them; Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling there together the greateſt patt of his life in this world.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The virgin mother obſerueth and keepeth in her hart al the doings, and ſayings of our Sauiour; diligently medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating thereupon.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="creed">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21013:21"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Caepit IESVS facere et decere.</head>
                        <figDesc>Jesus preaching to a crowd</figDesc>
                        <head>CREDO IN DEVM PATREM.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21013:21"/>
                  <p>THe eternal Sonne of God, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created wiſdome of the Father, our Lord and Sauiour, hauing taken vpon him the forme of à ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, eſteemed vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly à carpenter, and a carpenters ſonne and as altogether vnlerned, in the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith yere of his age, bidding his mother farewel, being now to dwel no more in her familie, goeth to Iohn the Baptiſt, and is baptized of him in Iordan. And thence he departeth preſently into the deſert, there faſteth (not eating nor drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king anie thing at al) fourtie dayes and fourtie nights, then is tempted by the Diuel, and va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſheth him. Afterwards he manifeſteth him ſelf to the world; preacheth pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; calleth diſciples; And by good life, heauenlie doctrine and miracles, draweth vnto him i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>numerable folowers; He inſtiteth the Sacrament of Baptiſme, for the Remiſſion of ſinnes (wherof Iohns Baptiſme was only a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure) teacheth the perfection of iuſtice, namely of Almes deedes, Praying and Faſting. For which albeit the High Prieſts, Scribes, Phariſees, Saducees, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodians, and the reſt of the wicked, do diuers waies perſecute him, yet he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer theleſſe perſeuereth doing good to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21013:22"/> al; confuting their errors, reprouing their ſinnes, ſoluing their malicious and captious queſtions; derecting their calu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations, euen the ſecret cogitations of their hartes; and to auoide their vila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous purpoſes ſeeking to murder him, he flieth often from them, and that ſometimes miraculouſly. Finally hauing in this maner conuerſed in the world, three yeres and ſomething more (hauing alſo lately in his Tranſfiguratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhewed to certaine of his Apoſtles, ſome glimſe of his glorie) at laſt he entereth into Ieruſalem riding vpon an aſſe colt, his diſciples and the people triumphing, ſpreading their garments, and ſtrawing boughes of Palmes and other trees in the way, receiue him as their king, with ioyful acclamations; the children alſo crying in the Temple: HOSANNA TO THE SONNE OF DAVID. Bleſſed is he that cometh in the name of our Lord! HOSANNA in the hiegheſt! O King of Iſrael!</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="rosary">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21013:22"/>
               <head>The ſecond Roſarie of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Pſalter: reſembled to a redde roſe: containing fiue ſorowful Myſteries.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In nomine Patris, &amp; Filij <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> &amp; Spiritus Sancti.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Jesus crucified encircled by five roses</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD forbid that I ſhould glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſauing in the Croſſe of our Lord IESVS Chriſt: who humbled him ſelf, made obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto death, euen the death of the Croſſe.</p>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21013:23"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>1. Mys terium doloroſum.</head>
                        <figDesc>Jesus prays in Gethsemane while his apostles sleep</figDesc>
                        <head>1. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21013:23"/>
                  <head>Our Sauiours Agonie in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Gethſemanie.</head>
                  <p>Ovr Lord and Sauiour the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his paſſion, when he had eaten the Paſchal lambe with his twelue Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, taking water and a towel waſ heth al their feete. And then exhorting them to humilitie, and puritie of life, he inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuteth and adminiſtreth the moſt bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and Sacrifice of his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and bloud, in the formes of bread and wine. And withal inſtituting the Holie Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Orders, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles (for them ſelues and ſucceſſors) to do the ſame, that is, to conſecrate and offer in Sacrifice, his bodie and bloud (being, according to the order of Melchi ſedech, the Sacrifice of the newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) til he come againe to iudge the world. Iudas then goeth out. And our Lord inſtructeth, exhorteth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the reſt, promiſeth them the Holie Ghoſt, praieth his Father for al the elect. And ſo goeth with the eleuen Apoſtles into the garden of Gethſemani. which place Iudas alſo knew, for that our Lord vſed to goe often thither with his diſciples.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21013:24"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our lord entring into the garden with his diſciples, ſaid to them: Sitte you here, whileſt I goe yonder and pray.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IESVS taking Peter, Iames and Iohn, a litle further, beginning to waxe ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſad, ſaith to them: My ſoul is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful euen to death: abide here, and watch with me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And parting alſo from theſe three a ſtones caſt, he prayeth ſaying: My FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER if it be poſſible, let this chalice paſſe from me. but yet not my wil, but thine be done.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IESVS cometh to his diſciples, and finding them aſleepe, ſaith to Peter: Euen ſo? Simon ſleepeſt thou? couldſt thou not watch one houre with me? watch ye and pray, that ye enter not into tentation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He goeth from them againe, and prayeth as before: MY FATHER if it be poſſible, take this chalice from me. yet not as I wil, but as thou wilt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21013:24"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He cometh againe and findeth them ſleeping: for their eyes were very heauie, and they wiſt not what they ſhould an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him. <hi>Neither ſaith he anie thing to them</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Leauing them he goeth againe, and prayeth the third time, the ſelf ſame prayer: MY FATHER, if it be poſſible, take this chalice from me. yet not my wil, but thine be done.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And there appeareth to him <hi>(either al the three times, or at leaſt the laſt time)</hi> an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel from heauen, ſtrengthening him. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>ſingular humilitie! the Lord of al is comforted by his ſeruant, the Creatour by his creature!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And whileſt he prayeth long in agonie, HIS SWEATE BECOME THAS DROPPES OF BLOVD, trickling downe vpon the ground.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Coming the third time he ſaith: ſleepe ye now and take reſt <hi>(ſhortly after)</hi> it ſufficeth, the houre is come: behold, the Sonne of man ſhalbe betrayed into the handes of ſinners; riſe, let vs go: behold, he that ſhal betray me is at hand.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21013:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>2. <hi>Mysterium doloroſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Jesus is scourged</figDesc>
                        <head>2. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21013:25"/>
                  <head>Our Sauiours apprehenſion, contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melious handling, and moſt cruel vvhipping.</head>
                  <p>AS our Lord and Sauiour was yet ſpeaking behold the traitour Iudas Iſcariote one of the twelue cometh, and with him a great troupe with lanterns, torches, ſwordes and other weapons, who al at the voice of IESVS ſaying: I AM HE, going backward fal to the ground, yet he ſuffereth them to riſe againe. And Iudas ſaluting his Maſter with a kiſſe (which was the ſigne to know him from his Apoſtles) they lay handes vpon IESVS. Peter draweth his ſworde, and cutteth of the right eare of Malchus, one of the high Prieſts ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Which our Sauiour preſently reſtoring, and healing, biddeth Peter put. vp his ſworde into the ſcabbard; for that it is his Fathers wil, he ſhal now ſuffer for al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind, otherwiſe he could haue manie legions of Angels to defend him, if that were more agreable to Gods goodnes, and mans ſaluation. Then the diſciples leauing their maiſter, runne al away. And ſo is the prophecie fulfilled: <hi>I vvil ſtrike the ſhepheard, and the ſheepe ſhalbe ſcattered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21013:26"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IESVS being bound is firſt brought to Annas, then to Caiphas. By them both he is examined of his diſciples, and of his doctrine, falſly accuſed, and ſtrooken on the face by à ſeruant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Caiphas adiureth our Sauiour to tel him, if he be Chriſt the Sonne of God; who anſwering that he is ſo, they iudge him a blaſphemer, and guiltie of death; vſing him moſt ſpitefully and cruelly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Moſt baſe fellowes do ſpitt in the face of Chriſt our Lord; they ſtrike him with their fiſtes, and couering his eyes beat him, and bid him read, who is it that ſtriketh thee?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>In the meane time Peter denieth our Lord thriſe. but IESVS looking vpon him, he goeth forth of the palace, and weepeth bitterly. The Iewes calling à councel, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne IESVS as guiltie of death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Early in the morning the chiefe of the Iewes, with their whole councel deliuer IESVS, priſoner to Ponce Pilate, Caeſars deputie. <hi>Then Iudas, ſeing that</hi> IESVS <hi>is condemned to die, hangeth him ſelfe deſperatly.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:21013:26"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Pilate aſking what accuſation they bring againſt him, they ſay: if he wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not a malefactor, we would not deliuer him vnto thee. Pilate teſtifying his i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, they wil nedes haue him crucified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Then they accuſe him, of ſubuerting theit nation, of forbidding to pay tribute to Ceſar, and of calling him ſelf king. not anſwering at al to the firſt two (being fri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uolous) he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth, that he is à king, but his kingdome is not of this world.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Pilat perceiuing that Chriſt is of Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee, ſendeth him to Herod, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded many curious queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, mocked as à foole, and ſent backe to Pilat.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Pilat biddeth the people chooſe of two only, either Barabbas or IESVS to be deliuered; they chooſe Barabbas. he offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth them alſo IESVS, but they al crie; Away with him, and geue vs Barabbas.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Pilat (to mollifie their ſtonie hartes) cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth our B. Sauiour to be ſo cruelly vvhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, that from the head to the foote al his bodie is torne thervvith, <hi>rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iuing (as is ſaid to haue bene reueled to S. Brigitte) 5490 vvoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in one day.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21013:27"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>3. <hi>Mys terium doloroſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Jesus is crowned with thorns</figDesc>
                        <head>3. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21013:27"/>
                  <head>The crovvning of our Sauiour vvith thornes, and his condemnation to be crucified.</head>
                  <p>AFter that our Sauiour is moſt cruelly whipped, the ſouldiars bring him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the court of the palace, where (as to à ſcorneful ſtage play) the whole band co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming together, they mocke both him and the whole natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Iewes, in ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon their poore and miſerable title of a King and Kingdome. They pul of againe his owne clothes, and put on his bodie (al imbrued with bloud) à purple garment. Then platting a crowne of horrible ſtrong and ſharpe thornes, they put the ſame on his tender and moſt ſacred head. And leauing nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, that may ſerue either to ſcorne or torment him, they put à reede in his right hand, and ſo ſetting him in à high place, bowing their knee in deriſion ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute him, ſaying; HAILE KING OF THE IEWES. And withal moſt ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully defile his moſt ſacred face with their abominable ſpitle, beating him alſo with their fiſtes, as the Iewes had done the night before.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21013:28"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>They take the reede out of his hand, and ther with beate the crowne of thor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes into his head; forcing therby more ſacred bloud to burſt out, and runne ouer al his bodie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Pilat ſuppoſing that the ſight hereof ſhould moue the Iewes to ſo much pitie as to ſpare his life, bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth forth our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour thus arayed, into the vtter court.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>So ſhewing him, in his purple garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with his crowne of thorns on his head, a reede in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, al his bodie miſerably torne, and imbrued with bloud, ſaith to the Iewes, BEHOLD THE MAN.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The high Prieſts and the people crie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud, Crucifie him, crucifie Him, <hi>as if they ſaid,</hi> Thou haſt now wel begun, hold on, crucifie him: for this maner of whipping wel beſemeth one that is to be crucified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Pilat moued with this crueltie in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſaith, Take you him, and crucifie him: for I find no cauſe to do it. They reply, that die he muſt, and he muſt be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21013:28"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Iewes ſeeing Pilat for al their importunitie not diſpoſed to crucifie Chriſt; they threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him with his allege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to Caeſar, crying: If thou releaſe this man, thou art not Caeſars freind.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Pilat hearing this new crie, bringeth forth IESVS, and ſitteth againe in the iudgements ſeate reſoluing rather to put Chriſt to death, though he know him to be moſt innocent, then to hazard his credite with Caeſar.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Yet once more he ſheweth IESVS to the Iewes, exprobrating and ſaying: Lo here your king. they crie, Away, away with him, crucifie him, we haue no king but Caeſar.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing al this nothing preuaileth, he waſheth his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, proteſting before the people; I am innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the bloud of this iuſt man: looke ye to it. the people crie: His bloud be vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>So Pilat ouercome vvith clamour of the people, and vvith feare of Caeſar, geueth ſentence, that IESVS OF NAZARETH KING OF THE IEVVES be nailed vpon the croſſe, and there hang vntil he be dead</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21013:29"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>4. <hi>Mys cerium doloroſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Jesus falls while carrying the cross</figDesc>
                        <head>4. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21013:29"/>
                  <head>Our Sauiour carieth his Croſſe tovvards Caluarie.</head>
                  <p>THE ſouldiars leade our Sauiour (now condemned to death) from the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate into the court of the palace, vvhere they cal againe together the vvhole band, and pulling of the purple robe, which ſticked faſt in his former vvoundes, they drawe our more freſh bloud, and put on him his owne clothes, but leaue the crowne of thornes faſt fixed in his head, both for his greater torment, and greater ignominie, leſt perhaps he might appeare like no king at al, or ſhould lacke à pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, to reſt his hèad on, hanging on the Croſſe. And hauing in the meane time prepared à moſt terrible heauie Croſſe, they lay the ſame vpon his ſore ſhoulders, to carie to the mount of Caluarie; tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting him by the ſight and vveight of ſo huge à burden, before he come to be nailed theron. And yet much heauier to him is the continual meditation of our ſinnes, for vvhich he ſuffereth al this, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially our ingratitude, in that vve neither go about to imitate his example in taking vp our croſſes, and folowing him, not yet duly conſider, vvhat he hath done for vs his miſerable creatures and vnvvorthie ſeruants.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21013:30"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>So IESVS going forth of the citie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayling vnder the croſſe our ſinnes, marketh the way as he paſſeth with his owne bloud, that whoſoeuer wil folow him, may not miſſe of the right path of his ſteppes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>His moſt ſacred mother, the immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late virgin (carying alſo her moſt heauie croſſe of compaſsion) meeteth our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, whoſe ſight and preſence greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth his former ſorowe and paine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our Lord being now weake of bodie and extreme wearie after ſo great trauel and loſſe of bloud, falleth downe groue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the ground, vnder his Croſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The cruel tormenters beate our ſweet Sauiour (lying on the ground as à meke lambe, or à poore worme, and not à ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) and ſpurne him with their feete, thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and haling him forward.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Yet fearing he ſhould die in the way, and ſo eſcape death on the Croſſe, they compel one Simon Cyrenean to carie the Croſſe of Chriſt, the reſt of the way to Caluarie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21013:30"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>A great multitude of people folow IESVS: among which certaine deuour women bewayle and lament him, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing how vniuſtly he is tormented, who did hurt to none at al, and good to verie manie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IESVS turning to them ſaith: Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Ieruſalem weepe not vpon me, but weepe vpon your ſelues, and vpon your children. For the daies ſhal come, when al Ieruſalem ſhalbe more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then now yee thinke me to be.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>A ſpecial deuout woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, called Vero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica, reacheth him à handkerchiefe, to wipe his face with al, being al embrued with ſweate and bloud, and with filthie ſpitle of the abhominable tormenters.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our Lord geueth her the handkerchiefe againe, not fowle (as might be expected) but al faire, and in it the moſt comfortable image of his owne ſweete viſage expreſſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our Sauiour cometh to Caluarie: à place execrable, ful of carkaſes and dead mens bones, in vvhich none but notorious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors vſed to be crucified. <hi>Here manie thinke, that Adam vvas buried.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:21013:31"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>5. <hi>Mysterium doloroſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Jesus is crucified</figDesc>
                        <head>5. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:21013:31"/>
                  <head>Our Sauiours crucifying, and death vpon the Croſſe.</head>
                  <p>COming to the toppe of mount Calua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, in ſteede of ſuch confortable good wine as vſually was geuen, to refreſh and ſtrengthen the hartes of them that were to die, they geue vnto our ſwete Sauiour (al vvearied and afflicted) vinegre mingled vvith myrrhe and gal, vvhich vvhen he had taſted, he vvould not drinke. Then againe rhey pul of al his clothes, with ſuch furie and fiercenes, as bringeth more bloud out of the innumerable vvoundes of his ſacred bodie, and ſo racking his armes and legges, vvith great violence to the length of the Croſſe, vvith manie knockes of ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers they naile him faſt therunto, pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing through the moſt tender vaines, ſine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vves, fleſh and bones, of both his handes, and both his feete, vvith great and rugh nailes. And for more reproch and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minie, they place our B. Sauiour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> betwen two theenes, as though he were the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedeſt of them al, and put a title ouer his heade, containing his name, his countrie, and the cauſe of his death, vvritten in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Greeke and Latin, IESVS OF NAZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RETH KING OF THE IEWES. And ſo they ſet vp the Croſſe, the foote falling into à hole made for that purpoſe.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21013:32"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider now my ſoul, and thinke with thy ſelf, hovv al his holie bodie is miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſhaken, and vvhat fluddes of moſt pretious bloud, do runne forth of thoſe foure great vvoundes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>What ſorovv alſo it is to our Sauiour to heare the Prieſtes, Elders, Scribes and others, both of the greateſt and vileſt ſorte to blaſpheme him, novv hanging on the Croſſe, for their ſakes, and for al mankind.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Meditate alſo his moſt perfect charitie, vvho not only prayeth for al the vvorld, but alſo particularly for thoſe that novv crucifie him, and blaſpheme him, ſaying: FATHER FORGEVE THEM, FOR THEY KNOVV NOT VVHAT THEY DOE.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Likevviſe conſider, and admire his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding mercie tovvardes paenitents, ſo graciouſly grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting to the poenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t theefe, more then he aſketh, ſaying; THIS DAY THOV SHALT BE WITH ME IN PARADISE.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And much more maiſt thou admire the depth of his loue, tovvards al iuſt perſons, and namely towards his deere mother, and beloued diſciple, vvhom he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth ech to other, ſaying to her, BEHOLD THY SONNE, and to him, BEHOLD THY MOTHER.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:21013:32"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Great darknes continuing three houres together, al are aſtoniſhed. Chriſt as man offereth him ſelf in Sacrifice to God: and that in extreme paines. vvhich at laſt he expreſſeth ſaying: My GOD, MY GOD, VVHY HAST THOV FOR SAKEN ME?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our Lord afflicted with bodelie drynes and moſt ſollicitous to ſaue mankind, ſaith: I THIRST: <hi>his fleſh in dede deſiring to be refreſhed vvith drinke, and his ſpirite to be recreated vvith the ſaluation of ſoules.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>They vvrappe a ſponge ful of vinegre, in hyſſope, &amp; offer it to his mouth. which out ſvveete Lord mekely taking, ſaith: IT IS CONSVMMATE.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Hauing therfore acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed al accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods ordinance for mankind, vvith ſtrong and loud voice he ſayeth: FATHER INTO THY HANDES I COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MEND MY SPIRITE.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And ſo preuenting death, though he could haue liued longer, bowing his heade he geueth vp the ghoſt: <hi>fulfilling that him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf had ſaid before, No man taketh my life avvay from me, but I yelde it of my ſelfe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="creed">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:21013:33"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Erit ſepulchrum eius glorioſum.</head>
                        <figDesc>Jesus is taken down from the cross</figDesc>
                        <head>CREDO IN DEVM.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21013:33"/>
                  <p>AT what time the Sonne of God dyed vpon the Croſſe, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of mankind, it pleaſeth alſo the ſame Diuine power, inteſtimonie and confirmation of ſo vvnderful a Myſterie, to ſhewe ſundrie miraculous and ſtrange euents, apparent to the whole world. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the Creator of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, by the iniurie of his creatures, hanging on the Croſſe, the earth is al darkened at midday, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing three whole houres together, by ecclips of the ſune, aboue al courſe of nature, ouer al the earth at once, and that in the fulmoone. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> After vvhich, the author of life before nature co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelleth, yeldeth vp the ghoſt, at his owne wil, vvhich no other liuing creature can do. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Then the veile of the Temple is rent in two peeces, from the toppe euen to the bottome. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The earth doth quake. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The rockes are torne in peeces. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues are opened; and (after our Lords re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection) manie bodies of the Saincts, that had ſlept, do riſe, and appeare to manie. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The Capitaine and ſouldiars, vvhoſe hartes vvere eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> novv hardened vvith malice, going avvay confeſſe openly, that in deede this man is the Sonne of God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> And manie of the moſt obſtinate Iewes goe alſo avvay repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting, and ſtriking them ſelues on the breſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> A ſouldiar vvith a ſpeare pearcing his ſide incontinent there cometh forth bloud
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21013:34"/> and water. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Ioſeph of Aramathia, a noble Senatour, who before, durſt not profeſſe him ſelf a diſciple of Chriſt, now goeth boldly to Pilate, and beggeth his bodie, and ſo taketh it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> In which holie worke an other principal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Ievves, called Nicodem' (vvho vvas vvo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to reſort to Chriſt by night, not daring ſo do in the day) ioyning him ſelf, brought a mixture of myrrhe and aloes, about an hundreth pounds. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> To al vvhich miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, happening at the death of out Sauiour, thou maiſt iuſtly adde in thy meditation, the ſingular modeſtie, in uincible courage, moſt heroical fortitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and vnſpeakeable pietie of the ſacred virgin, his mother. Who ſeeing vvith her eyes, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d feeling in her ovvne hart al that paſſed, and vvas done and ſuffered by her only ſvveete ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne; yet admitteth nor committeth no act vnſemely to her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and moſt high perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in al vertues but taking into her ovvne armes the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad bodie of her former ioy and life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvaileth the ſame, &amp; deliuering it again aſſiſteth in burying therof. And ſo the precious bodie enbalmed vvith ſpices, and vvrapped in fine linnen, is buried in à nevv monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t made in à rocke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in none hath bene laid before, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great ſtone is rolled to the doore, vvhich alſo the Ievves by permiſſion of Pilate, ſeale vp, and ſet a gard of vvatch men, to kepe the ſepulchre, leſt his diſciples ſteale him avvay, &amp; ſay, he is riſen from death.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="rosary">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:21013:34"/>
               <head>The third Roſaire of our Ladies Pſalter: reſembled to a damaſke roſe: containing fiue glorious Myſteries.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In nomine Patris, &amp; Filij <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> &amp; Spiritus Sancti.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>the risen Christ encircled by five roses</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Lord IESVS Chriſt was obedient vnto death: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the death of the Croſſe. For the which God hath exalted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, and hath geuen him à name, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s aboue al names.</p>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21013:35"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>1. <hi>Myst<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>erium glorioſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Christ rises from the tomb</figDesc>
                        <head>1. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:21013:35"/>
                  <head>The Reſurrection of our Lord.</head>
                  <p>THE moſt holie, and euer glorious ſoule of our Lord and Sauiour, leauing his bodie dead on the Croſſe, goeth incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent into the lake called Limbus Patrum by whoſe preſence the ſoules of the Saincts of the old Teſtament (hitherto kept in darcknes) are repleniſhed with moſt cleare light, incomparable gladnes and ioy, receiuing their long expected beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, vvhich conſiſteth in the viſion of God. And ſo our Sauiour there performeth that which he promiſed the penitent thefe ſaying: <hi>This day thou ſhall be vvith me in Paradiſe.</hi> The third day (ſhortly after midnight, as the ancient Fathers of the Church do thinke) the ſame moſt glorious ſoule returning into the bodie, both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther making à perfect man, cometh forth of the graue vvithout opening the ſame. And by and by an Angel deſcending from heauen, remoueth the ſtone from the doore of the monument, and ſitteth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Wherat the vvatchmen are frighted, and running into the cittie tel the High Prieſts that vvhich had happened. Who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſembling together vvith the Elders in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouncel, geue à great ſumme of money to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e ſouldiars, to ſay, that his diſciples came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y night and ſtole him away, vvhen they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vere a ſleepe.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:21013:36"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>In the meane time our glorious Sauiour appeareth to his deare mother, before al others meriting this conſolation. <hi>As al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Chriſtians may eaſely conceiue, though the ſame (as needles) be not recorded in the vvritten Goſpel.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>To holie Magdale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and other two, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to annoint the bodie, an Angel teſtifieth, that he is riſen: ſhe runneth to tel the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and returneth vvith them: they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting againe our Lord appeareth to her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He appeareth againe to holie Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene, and to the other two returning ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mewards, they adore him, and he biddeth them go tel his diſciples, that they ſhal ſee him in Galilee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The ſame day he appeareth to S. Peter, and confirmeth him in faith. Perhaps alſo to S. Iohn, for his conſolation. for he, after he ſawe the ſepulchre, beleeued. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 20.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Likewiſe our Sauiour appeareth to S Iames the iuſt, called our Lords brother <hi>as it is moſt like the ſame day. for it is ſaid, the after the chalice of our Lord, he did neither eat nor drinke, til he had ſeene him riſen from death</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21013:36"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The ſame day he appeareth to tvvo diſciples going towards Emaus, talking of him but not beleeuing his Reſurrection, til (hauing inuited him as à ſtranger) they knowe him in breaking of bread.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame euening our Lord appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to tenne of the Apoſtles gathered together, the doores being ſhutt. Only Thomas being abſent wil not beleue the reſt of the Apoſtles telling him, that they had ſeene our Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The eight day our Lord appeareth again to the eleuen Apoſtles, and ſaith to Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas. Put here thy finger into the holes of my hands, and thy hand into my ſide, and be not incredulous, but faithful. Thomas anſwereth: MY LORD, AND MY GOD.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Againe our lord appeareth to Peter, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, Iohn, Thomas, Nathanael, and other two, at the ſea of Tiberias. There he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Peter his Vicar general in earth, and chiefe Paſtor of his Church; vvithal fortel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him that he ſhalbe crucified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He appeareth againe to the eleuen in Galilee, where he commandeth them to preach the Goſpel, and miniſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments in al the world, promiſing to aſſiſt them by his Spirite, til the worlds end.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:21013:37"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>2. <hi>Myſterium gloriosum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>the Ascension of Christ</figDesc>
                        <head>2. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:21013:37"/>
                  <head>The Aſcenſion of our Lord.</head>
                  <p>HOw ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to what perſons our Lord and Sauiour appeared, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twen his Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, beſides the apparitions here to fore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, is vnknowne to al mortal creatu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res. Neuertheles we may not doubt, but he often appeared to his bleſſed mother, who for manie cauſes, beſt of al others, deſerued his moſt comfortable conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. And it is alſo vndoubtedly belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that he appeared ſomtimes to his ſeruants Enoch and Elias, as yet liuing in their mortal bodies, in the terreſtrial para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. And that he appeared often to his Apoſtles, and familiarly conuerſed vvith them, not only the Ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Fathers, but alſo the holie Scriptures do teſtifie, affirming that he ſhewed him ſelfe aliue to them, after his Paſſion in manie arguments, for fourtie daies appearing to them, and ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the kingdom of God. to vvit, of the Church, and of al functions and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be done therin. Amongſt other things, he inſtituteth the reſt of the ſeuen Sacraments, not inſtituted before, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth ful authoritie powre and commiſſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o his militant Church, for the bringing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oules into the Church triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſoules deliuered from Limbo, the meane while <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olowing him whither ſoeuer he goeth.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:21013:38"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Finally, the fourtith day after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, our lord appearing in Bethania vnto his Apoſtles (lately returned from Galilee) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth them not to depart from Ieruſalem, til they be endued with powre from aboue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He ſaith moreouer vnto them, that they ſhalbe witneſſes of his Paſſion, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and Remiſsion of ſinnes, in Ieruſalem, and in al Iurie, and Samaria, and eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the vt moſt part of the earth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>In the mount Oliuet our Lord now readie to aſcend into heauen, for his laſt farewel in earth, lifting vp his handes bleſſeth the whole Church, imparting his grace (as at diuers other times he did) by an external ſigne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Hauing thus beſtowed his bleſſing, he aſcendeth directly into heauen, a great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber beholding him, vntil he being couered with the clowdes, they loſe ſight of him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And vvhileſt they looke ſtil after him, if perhaps they may ſee him amiddes the clowdes, behold two Angels (in ſhape of men) ſtand by them in vvhite garments.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:21013:38"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Angels ſay vnto them: Ye men of Galilee, what ſtand ye looking into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? This IESVS vvho is aſſumpted from you into heauen, ſhal ſo come as you haue ſeene him going.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Then they al adoring him, goe from mount Oliuet into Ieruſalem, vvith great ioy thanking our Lord, for his vvonderful benefites, beſtowed and prepared for mans ſaluation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And being come into the citie, our B. Ladie the mother of our Lord, vvith the Apoſtles and other faithful, in al almoſt an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth and twentie, going vp into a cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, vvith one mind perſeuere in prayer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>There S. Peter as chiefe Paſtor of the vvhole companie, publiſheth an election to be made of an Apoſtle, to ſupplie ludas too me. <hi>VVich he doth not by anie commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt expreſſely vvritten, but by ſuggeſtion of Gods ſpirite, agreable to the Scriptures.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>They appoint two, Ioſeph and Mathias, and praying God to declare by directing of the lottes, vvhich of them he had choſen to the Apoſtle ſhippe, the lot falleth vpon Mathias, and he is numbred vvith the other eleuen Apoſtles.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:21013:39"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>3. <hi>Mysterium glorioſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>the Holy Ghost comes to the Apostles and Mary</figDesc>
                        <head>3. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21013:39"/>
                  <head>The Comming of the Holie Ghoſt</head>
                  <p>SEing the moſt holie virgin the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of God, ful of grace, the holie A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtles endued alſo with power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and al the faithful being alreadie iuſt, did neuertheles perſeuere praying tenne continual daies, for the comming of the Holie Ghoſt, promiſed them by our Sauiour: how much more ought we wretched ſinners, moſt fraile and weake veſſels, to perſeuere in pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce prayer and obſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we may receiue the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt, either for remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſinnes if yet we remayne in that ſtate, or for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace, if we be alreadie reſtored into Gods fauour? And here, ô my ſoule, thou oughteſt to be ſo much more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in meditating this Myſterie, becauſe here thine owne free co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent, and coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is neceſſarily required to thy iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; wheras in thy creation, rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, and vocation, thou diddeſt, nor couldeſt nothing at al further nor hinder Gods worke. But now except thou doeſt volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tarily accept of the grace offered thee, and cooperate therewith, thou ſhalt not only neuer attayne eternal life, but alſo incurre greater damnation, for ſo great benefites by thee neglected.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:21013:40"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The tenth day after the Aſcenſion, being the fiftith from Eaſter, the third houre (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſune riſing) ſodenly cometh à ſound from heauen, as of a vehement wind and filleth the whole houſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re they were praying.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And immediatly there appeare to them parted tongues, as it were of fire, which do light and reſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerie one of theſe 120. perſons, ſo praying together.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And they are al repleniſhed with the Holie Ghoſt receiuing abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t increaſe of grace, with the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gifts: of wiſdome, vnderſtanding, counſel, fortitude, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, pietie, and of the feare of our Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>This voice being heard the people flocking together of manie nations and diuers languages, euerie one heareth the Apoſtles ſpeake in his owne tongue, the great workes of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Some deriding ſay, Theſe men are ful of new vvine. But S. Peter confuteth this ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, prouing that IESVS, vvhom they had crucified, is riſen, and aſcended, and hath ſent the Holie Ghoſt. And 5000. are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and baptized.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:21013:40"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Apoſtles preach boldly Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, confirming their doctrine by Scri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptures, and miracles, notwithſtanding the Iewes commande them, and that vvith threates, not to ſpeake at al of IESVS.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Ananias and Sapphira for their ſacrilege, at S. Peters vvorde fal downe dead. Others are cured of diſeaſes euen by the ſhadowe of S. Peter, vvho vvith others being caſt in priſon, are deliuered by an Angel, and preach openly in the Temple.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>They are al apprehended againe and brought into the councel, indited for tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the commandement of the High Prieſts, but they anſwere, That God muſt be obeyed rather then men. Finally they are vvhipped, and therof they reioyce.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>S. Steuen (vvith ſix others) is made Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, preacheth Chriſt, vvorketh miracles, confoundeth the aduerſaries, is accuſed of blaſphemie, and ſtoned to death. But is crovvned in heauen. And manie, by his death and prayers, are conuerted.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The twelue Apoſtles make the Crede, and going into diuers partes of the vvorld preach the Goſpel. Saul à notorious perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor is conuerted, and made à chiefe Apoſtle. And ſo preacheth Chriſt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting manie nations.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:21013:41"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>4. <hi>Mysterium glorioſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Mary dies in bed</figDesc>
                        <head>4. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:21013:41"/>
                  <head>The death and Aſsumption of our B. Ladie.</head>
                  <p>VVhen the Apoſtles, according to their function, preach the Goſpel of Chriſt, and trauel in gaining ſoules (in diuers and ſpecially in theſe parts of the vvorld; Peter firſt in lurie, then in Syria, Antioche and other places, finally in Italie: Andrew in Achaia, Iames the greater in Spaine, Iohn in Aſia, Thomas in India, Iames the leſſe in Ieruſalem, Philip in Phrygia, Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew in Scythia, Matthew in Aethiopia, Simon in Perſia, Thadaeus in Meſopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, Matthias in Paleſtina, Paul in moſt parts of the world) the whole Church flooriſhing in al kinds of vertue, aboue al others the moſt ſacred virgin, the mother of God excelleth: vvho albe it ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently endued with diuine knowlege that ſhe teacheth the Euangeliſts manie things, concerning our Sauiours Incarnation, Natiuitie, education, and other like Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, beſt knowne to her of al mortal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; yet being a vvoman, and moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of al creatures, ſhe neither preacheth openly, nor conuerſeth with manie, but liueth in priuate ſtate, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual exerciſe of al vertues, leauing in the world by her vvhole life, a moſt perfect Rule and liuely example, to al thoſe that deſire to tend towards perfection.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:21013:42"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>After our Lords A ſcenſion, his B. mother our Ladie, being more frie, then euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, from vvorldly cares, imployeth her ſelfe vvholy to deuotion. S. Iohn the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt prouiding for her al neceſſaries tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and ſpiritual.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>After fifteene yeares more expectation, it is reueled to the ſacred virgin, that ſhe ſhal change her mortal life for life immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and ſo enioy the euerlaſting fruition of her bleſſed ſonne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She humbly beſeketh her ſonne our Lord, that he vvil voutchſafe to graunt her, the ſight of his Apoſtles, before ſhe part out of this tranſitorie life.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Al the Apoſtles at one inſtant are taken vp into the ayre, and brought into leruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, to viſite the B. virgin, except S. Iames already martyred, and Thomas vvho by Gods ſpecial prouidence cometh ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what later.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Apoſtles and other Apoſtolical men being thus met together, the moſt holie ſoule of the ſacred virgin, ſweetly parting from the bodie aſcendeth into heauen with à troupe of glorious Angels.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:21013:42"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Her ſacred bodie (of which God tooke fleſh) is moſt honorably buried in Geth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemani, with Apoſtolical and Angelical muſike, moſt heauenly melodie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The ſame Angelical quier remayneth three whole dayes at the ſepulchre, ſinging Pſalmes Hymnes and ſpiritual Canticles, prayſing God and the mother of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>After three dayes the Angels ceaſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and Thomas the Apoſtle arriuing, with moſt ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deuotion beſeketh the reſt of the Apoſtles, to graunt him the ſight of the moſt venerable and ſacred bodie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>To ſatisfie his deuote deſire they ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſepulchre. Where finding only the linnen, moſt ſweete and fragrant, in vvhich the holie bodie had bene wrapped, the bodie it ſelfe can nowhere be found in earth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Wherupon theſe ſo many and ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eye witneſſes do aſſuredly deme, that he who tooke fleſh of this imaculate bodie, hath aſſumpted the ſame into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united to the ſoul in eternal glorie.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decade">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:21013:43"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>5. <hi>Myſterium glorioſum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Mary is crowned in heaven by the Holy Trinity</figDesc>
                        <head>5. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:21013:43"/>
                  <head>The Coronation of our B. Ladie.</head>
                  <p>THE Apoſtles are againe reſtored to the places from whence they were brought: and by them and others the death and Aſſumption of the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate virgin, mother of God, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in al parts of the world. And ſo beginneth more and more to be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led that prophecie of hers, ſaying: FROM HENCE FORTH AL GENERATIONS SHAL CAL ME BLESSED. For euen from her Aſſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the whole Church of Chriſt bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as ſtil it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth) moſt ſolemly to celebrate, not only the aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of her moſt holie ſoul into heauen (as of other Saincts) but alſo the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection aſſumption and glorification of her bodie in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where ſhe enioying the perfect viſion of God, in the higheſt degree, after her ſonne of al creatures, is eſtabliſhed Quene of heauen, and of al bleſſed Saincts and Angels, adorned with ſo excellent à crowne, as no earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thing can expreſſe, though often prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured by diuers excellent things and perſons, but al infinitly inferior to the thing it ſelf.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:21013:44"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Quene of al holie Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and holie Angels: for that fhe in this life keeping in Matrimonial ſtate, Angelical puritie, was bleſſed with fruite wherby mankind is redeemed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Q. of holie widowes, and of Archangels: who being ſaluted by an Archangel, conceiued the ſonne of God; And afterward became an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple and conſolation of al faithful widows.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Q. of virgins, and Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Principalities: vvho ſo farre excelled al others in virginal puritie, as a Quene excelleth her ſubiects in princelie dignitie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Q. of al Religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and of Angelical Poteſtats: becauſe ſhe renouncing the vvorld, and by vowe of virginitie excluding the ordinarie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of conceiuing, conceiued by the Holie Ghoſt our Redemer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Q. of Euangeliſts, and of Angelical Powres: for that ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed euen the Euangeliſts in diuine Myſteries, and conceiued and bare him, vvho only is the author and vvorker of al miracles.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:21013:44"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Q. of al holie Biſſhops and Poſtors, and of Angelical Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: becauſe ſhe (by geuing her ſpecial aſſent to that the B. Trinitie had decreed) brought into the vvorld the bread of life, the true foode of ſoules.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Q. of Patriarches, and of the Angelical Thrones: for that ſhe by an ineffable meanes conceiued, and nine moneths bare in her wombe, the Sonne of God, her owne alſo proper ſonne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Q. of al holie Prophets, and of the holie Cherubims: for that ſhe more perfectly knew al diuine Myſteries (being the mother of God) then any other mere creature vvhoſoeuer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crovvned Q. of al Chriſts Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and Apoſtles, and of the burning Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphims: for that ſhe farre excelled them (vvherin they excel the reſt of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants) in feruent charitie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She therfore, vvho excelled in grace al orders of men and Angels, doth alſo excel the ſame in moſt high degree of glorie; and is placed and crowned, by her owne moſt excellent ſonne, the Quene of al creatures.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="creed">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:21013:45"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Omne iudic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>m dedit Filio: quia Filius Hominis eſt.</head>
                        <figDesc>Christ presides over the Final Judgment</figDesc>
                        <head>CREDO IN DEVM.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:21013:45"/>
                  <p>BE thankful (ô my ſoul) to the moſt B. Trinitie, one aeternal God: who created thee after his owne Image, to the end thou ſhouldeſt ſerue him, and therby inherite his heauenly kingdome. who alſo to redeme thee, being through ſinne become the bond ſlaue of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, and guiltie of aeternal death, and damnation, ſent his owne only Sonne (the ſecond Perſon of the ſame Holie Trinitie) to take fleſh of man and to be borne of à virgin, to liue in pouertie, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and worldlie miſeries: and finally to ſuffer the moſt ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and painful death of the Croſſe. who the third day roſe againe, for thy iuſtification: the fourtith day folowing aſcended into heauen, for thy glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; And after tenne dayes more, ſent the Holie Ghoſt (the third Perſon of the ſame moſt B. Trinitie) in viſible ſignes to his Church (the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beginning in Ieruſalem) to continue with the ſame Church, to the end of the world; that by his grace and operation, thou, and euerie ſoule, ſhouldeſt be made partaker of theſe ſo great benefites, ſo dearly purchaſed by our ſweete Sauiour. And in particular be thou moſt thankful, for that by this
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21013:46"/> grace of the Holie Ghoſt (which thou by no meanes couldeſt deſerue) thou art now a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the Catholike Church; and therby partaker of diuers Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and other moſt holie Myſteries, and of al the prayers and merites of the faithful in this world, yea and of al the court of heauen. By which graces alſo thou haſt bene waſhed from thy ſinnes, iuſtified and ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctified. and that not once only but often, thy Redemer not hitherto ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thee to die in thy ſinnes, as manie others haue done, but ſtil offereth thee his grace and ſweete pardon, readie to receiue thee, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and how often ſoeuer thou doeſt truly conuert, and ſincerely wilt accept thereof; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this inſtant, except thou thy ſelfe repel the ſame from thee. And finally, ſo thou perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in his ſeruice to the end, he wil geue vnto thee (my ſoule) ſhortly after death, and to my bodie for thy ſake, in the general iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day, when al fleſh ſhal riſe againe, an inae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable crowne of glorie, and life euerlaſting. AMEN.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="corone__rosary">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:21013:46"/>
               <head>The Corone of our B. Ladie: With certaine particular points to be meditated, in ſaying the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In nomine Patris, &amp; Filij <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> &amp; Spiritus Sancti.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mary encircled by a crown of thorns</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E mindful (ô my ſoul) of the Paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lord, and of the Compaſsion of our Ladie, his mother. Suffer thou with them in this world, that thou maiſt reigne with them in glorie.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:21013:47"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>In ſudore vultus tui, veſceris pane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </head>
                        <figDesc>Adam and Eve labor after the Fall</figDesc>
                        <head>1. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:21013:47"/>
                  <head>Certaine ſingular Priuilegies of the B. virgin Marie, before her Natiuitie.</head>
                  <p>THE aeternal vviſdom of God orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before al vvorldes, that Chriſt our Lord ſhould be borne of a virgin, die vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a croſſe, and therby redeme ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind from the captiuitie of ſinne and damnation, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which we fel by the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sgreſſion of A da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ordayned withal, that there ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the world, at the time deſigned, a certaine virgin excelling al other creatures euen the pure Angels, in grace and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who ſhould be the mother of this our Redemer. And by cooperating with him to our ſaluation, as old Eue had done with Adam to our fal and deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould do more then recompence the hurt of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. For as Adam was the proper and prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipal cauſe, and Eue the next occaſion of ſinne and death: ſo Chriſt is the only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cauſe, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his mother the next occaſion of grace and life. Wherupon ſaieth ſweete S. Bernard: Albeit by one man in deede and one woman, we were excedingly damaged yet (God be thanked) by one man and one woman al loſſes are repared. And that not without great increaſe of graces. For the benefite doth farre excede the loſſe. Our merciful Father geuing vs for à terreſtrial Adam Chriſt our Redemer; and for old Eue Gods owne mother.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:21013:48"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our merciful Lord promiſeth this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular virgin, ſtraight after the fal of man, ſaying to the ſerpent: <hi>I vvil put enmitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvven thée and the vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, betvven thy ſeede and her ſeede, but ſhe ſhal bruyſe thy head in peeces.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The firſt woman being by ſinne the mother of death, yet is called EVA, that is, the mother of the liuing, in figure of this bleſſed virgin, ordayned to be the Mother of life.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Likwiſe Sara, Rachael, Anne, Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth and others, being long barraine, but afterwards mothers of notable iſſue, are figures of this ſingular virgin the Mother of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The buſh alſo of Moyſes, Aarons rode Gedeons fleece, the arke of the couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the glaſſe without ſpot, the garden in cloſed, and other ſhadowes of the old Teſtament, doe ſignifie the ſame fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of this ſacred virgin.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And for other ſingular vertues of al ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſhe is prefigured by Rebecca, Marie the ſiſter of Moyſes, Debora, Iael, Iudith, Heſter and other moſt noble perſons, and things.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:21013:48"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Prophets do moſt cleerly fortel this bleſſed virgin: A rodde ſhal ſpring of the roote of Ieſſe: A virgin ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and beare a ſonne: A woman ſhal enuiron a man. And manie the like.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>This ſingular ſpouſe of God is likewiſe deſcribed by Salomon: A lilie amongſt thornes: Al bewtiful: Faire as the moone: Choſen as the ſunne: The ſea ſtarre. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Of this meruelous virgin the Sybilles (Phrophetiſſes of God among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens) do thus ſing: <hi>(vves nigh: Novv comes the virgin cleare, the golden age dra-Nevv Ofſpring doth appeare, ſent from the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auens high, VVhich is Gods iſſue deare.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Anne the wife of Ioachim, after twentie yeares barrainnes, conceiueth by Gods ſpecial fauour this noble virgin, ſo often promiſed, prefigured, prophecied, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore al worlds elected the Mother of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>And leſt ſhe ſhould be at anie time, the child of vvrath, Gods enemie, or ſlaue of the diuel, ſhe is by ſingular priuilege (as manie piouſly thinke) preſerued from al ſinne, and vvith the infuſion of her ſoul repleniſhed vvith grace.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:21013:49"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e eſt iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> progreditur quaſi aurora couſurg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
                        <figDesc>Mary's nativity</figDesc>
                        <head>2. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:21013:49"/>
                  <head>The Natiuitie of the B. virgin; and her life til ſhe vvas eſpouſed.</head>
                  <p>LIke as the morning driuing away the nights darknes, beſides the light which it bringeth, for ſheweth à greater light to be at hand: euen ſo after foure thouſand yeares darknes in the whole world, firſt ſhineth the moſt pure virgin voide of al ſinne, and ful of grace: plainly ſignifying by her ſingular vertues, the true light and fountaine of al grace (which lightned her, and al that be light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) to be very nere at hand. For now is borne the ſingular ſpouſe, ordayned to be the mother of God, who was ſo long ſince promiſed to her noble Anceſters; prefigured by manie miraculous Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; for told by Prophetical oracles; the renowned virgin without ſpott, borne of the bleſſed ſeede of the Patriarkes, of the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t race of the Prophets; of the holie ſtock of Leui, and of the Royal bloud of Iuda; euerie way adorned with al kind of generoſitie, and endued in the higheſt degree with moſt cleare ſanctitie becauſe ſhe is to conceiue, and beare the fountaine and flowre, the beginning and end of moſt holie and true Nobilitie.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:21013:50"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>This virgin is called MARIA, that is, The ſea, Bitternes of the ſea, Miſtreſſe and Ladie of the ſea, or Exalted. Wherby are noted diuerſe things happening vnto her, ioyful, ſorowful, and glorious.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Coming to the vſe of reaſon and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſeriouſly of God, ſhe dedicateth her whole life to his ſeruice, firmly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing neuer to offend him more nor leſſe, in thought, word, nor deede.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>At the age of three yeares ſhe is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in the Temple: where (alacritie of mind ſupplying imbecillitie of bodie) ſhe aſcendeth the fiftene ſtepps before the dore without helpe of anie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>From morning til nine a clock ſhe is only occupied in Diuine ſeruice: thence til noone in handie vvork. After meat (being very ſmal) ſhe imployeth the reſt of the day in reading ſacred bookes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Her vvhole life (as a moſt perfect rule of al perfection) ſhineth in al vertues: namely in humilitie, obedience, prudence, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, grauitie: in ſingular faith, hope, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and contempt of the vvorld.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:21013:50"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The vertue of virginitie (hitherto vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne in the world) ſhe doth ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly obſerue therto binding her ſelf for euer by religious vowe: as alſo to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie and obedience.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is of al chaſt perſons moſt chaſt, of al good the beſt, of al vviſe the vviſeſt, of religious the moſt religious, amongſt al ſhe onlie attayneth the ful perfection of Religious ſtate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She attayneth alſo to that ſpecial know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Gods counſel, amongſt other Myſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries reueled vnto her, that God ſhal be borne of a virgin, and by death vpon the Croſſe ſhal redem mankind.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Wherupon ſhe deſireth aboue al, that ſhe may once ſee this our Redemer, and that ſhe may be admitted to imploy her humble ſeruice to that moſt noble virgin his mother.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Being by the Prieſts (her Superiors) eſpouſed to Ioſeph (a godlie yong man) ſhe ſignifieth to him her vowe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual virginitie. Wherof he alloweth ſo wel, that he alſo voweth perpetual chaſtitie.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:21013:51"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>it m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> magna qui potens eſt.</head>
                        <figDesc>the Wise Men present Mary and child with gifts</figDesc>
                        <head>3. PATER NOSTER</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:21013:51"/>
                  <head>The Annunciation with other Myſteries to the Purification.</head>
                  <p>AL things being accompliſhed that ſhould go before the coming of Meſſias, the moſt bleſſed Trinitie ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth an Embaſſadour Gabriel an Archangel, or (as ſome holie Doctors thinke) one of the high Seraphins, to the moſt gracious virgin Marie, as it may ſeeme for three ſpecial cauſes. Firſt, to ſignifie vnto her in the behalfe of God almightie, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of heauen and earth, that ſhe ſhal conceiue and beare the Sonne of God, that is, the ſecond Perſon of the ſame moſt holie Trinitie, the long promiſed SAVIOVR of the world. Secondly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, to the effectuating hereof, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the ſame bleſſed virgin, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the Diuine goodnes wil not accompliſh this moſt excellent worke. Thirdly, that by Angelical teſtimonie this great Myſterie may be notified to the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le vvorld, vvhich is ſo ioyful to Angels and men. For by this meanes Angels receiue à Head, by vvhom the ruine of their felowes is to be repared. And men enioy à Rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, by vvhom al mankind is to be ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed from captiuitie of ſinne, and of euerlaſting death.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:21013:52"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The holie virgin being in contemplatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Angel vnexpected ſaluteth her ſaying: HAILE FVL OF GRACE, OVR LORD IS WITH THEF: BLESSED ART THOV AMONG WOMEN. wherat ſhe is trubled.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Feare not MARIE (ſaith the Angel) for thou haſt found grace vvith God. Behold thou ſhalt conceiue and beare à ſonne, and ſhalt cal his name IESVS. He ſhal be great, and ſhal be called the Sonne of the Hiegheſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She then demanding, by what meanes ſhe ſhal conceiue, ſeing not by man, the Angel anſwereth: The Holie Ghoſt ſhal come vpon thee, and the powre of the Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gheſt ſhal ouerſhadow thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The B. Virgin anſwering againe: <hi>Behold the handmaide of our Lord, be it donne to me according to thy vvord:</hi> the Sonne of God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the ſame inſtant made the Sonne of man, and the virgin is made the mother of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Preſently ſhe viſiteth her coſine Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, at vvhoſe coming the Infant in Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeths vvombe leapeth for ioy of Chriſts preſeuce. And the mother admireth the great humilitie of the Mother of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:21013:52"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The B. virgin, after three moneth, returning home, appeareth to be with childe: Ioſeph is therwith trubled, but an Angel telleth him, that ſhe hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by the Holie Ghoſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>They go to Bethleem according to an Edict made by Caeſar. There our Lord is borne, and laid in a manger; the Angel, ſing, the ſhepheards viſitie the Infant, and gloriſie God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The eight day the child is circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed, and his name called IESVS, <hi>a name that is aboue al names.</hi> For God in geuing vs. SAVIOVR, powreth as it were vpon vs al his owne bountifulnes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Three Sages, ſeeing à ſtrange and bright ſtarre appeare, come from the Eaſt to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem, ſeeking the king of the Iewes. And finding him in Bethleem, they offer vnto him gold, myrrhe, and frankincence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The moſt pure virgin (not obliged therto) obſerueth the ceremonie of Purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, preſenteth her ſonne in the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. Where Simeon ioyfully receiueth him into his armes. Yet fortelleth the mother of ſorowes to come.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:21013:53"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Virgula ex ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>matibus mvrrhae et thurts.</head>
                        <figDesc>Mary and Joseph rest during flight from Herod</figDesc>
                        <head>4. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21013:53"/>
                  <head>The moſt ſpecial tribulations and comforts of our Ladie, from her Purification to the Paſsion of our Lord.</head>
                  <p>HErod ſeeking to kil our Sauiour in his infancie, Ioſeph vvarned in ſleepe by an Angel to flie into Aegipt vvith the child and his mother, preſently parteth away the ſame night. In vvhich baniſhement for their ſuſtenance, ſomething the holie virgin gaineth by ſpinning and ſowing, ſomething Ioſeph getteth by his carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters art, the reſt they receiue of almes, ſo much as ſufficeth for their ſtate of pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which they profeſſe. For hauing meate and clothes in very meane ſorte, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire no more. And as vvel in Aegypt, as after and before, in this happie familie alwaies remaineth, vvith ſingular peace, à moſt holie contention. For that euerie perſon humbling them ſelues, vvil needes be much inferior to the other two. IESVS being in deede Lord of heauen and earth, yet liueth ſubiect to his mother, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed father. the B. virgin nouriſhing and tending her owne ſonne, yet honoreth him, as he is alſo the Sonne of God; and obeyeth Ioſeph as her head and Lord. Ioſeph helpeth and directeth them both in temporal affayres; yet vvith al humble and due reuerence honoreth the Sonne as Lord and king; and the mother as Ladie and Quene of men and Angels.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:21013:54"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Herod being dead, Ioſeph returneth vvith the childe and his mother into the Land of Iſrael: but fearing ARchelaus his ſonne and ſucceſſor in Iudea, they dwel in Nazareth in Galilee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IESVS being tvvelue yeares old remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in Ieruſalem vnknowne to his pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Who ſeeking him at night amongſt their kinſfolke, and not finding him, returne the next day, and ſeeke him in Ieruſalem.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>After three daies they find him in the Temple ſitting amongſt the Doctors, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them and aſking queſtions. To his mother he anſwereth, that he muſt be about his Fathers buſines.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The thirtith yeare of his age he taketh leaue of his mother, as no more to dwel with her. About this time Ioſeph dieth. And ſo the mother virgin and widow dwelleth with her coſines.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our Lord is baptized of Iohn, faſteth fourtie daies: Then calleth diſciples, and preacheth the kingdom of God; And at his mothers inſtance turneth water into wine at à Mariage.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:21013:54"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She moſt deuoutly heareth her ſonne Diuine Sermons: often ſeeth his Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: diligently obſerueth the diuers affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of men, and continually medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpon al.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>A certaine woman, burſting out in middes of the troupe, in praiſe of Chriſt and of his mother, ſayeth: Bleſſed is the wombe that bare thee, and the pappes that gaue thee ſucke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Wherunto our Lord ioyneth greater praiſe, ſaying: Yea bleſſed are they that heare the word of God, and keepe it. <hi>As much to ſay: as my mother is more bleſſed for hearing me, then for hearing me.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing manie thouſandes folow and admire her ſonne, and others buſie to deſtroy him, ſhe remayneth ſtil in one ſtate, knowing farre greater matters are yet to come.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Whileſt others receiue our Lord with triumph into Ieruſalem, as their King, onlie his deare mother meditateth vpon his Paſſion, which he is to ſuffer within fewe daves after.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:21013:55"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Tuam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap> animam pertranſibit gladius.</head>
                        <figDesc>Mary observes Jesus on the cross</figDesc>
                        <head>5. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:21013:55"/>
                  <head>The Compaſsion of our Ladie: at our Lords Paſsion and death.</head>
                  <p>VVhat à ſacred ftorehouſe of al vertues the B. virgin is, doth abundantly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in her vvhole life, but moſt ſpecially in the time of her ſonne our Lord his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and death. Where aboue al other vertues, her feruent charitie (Quene of al the reſt) doth moſt excel: which neither the obſtinate rancor of the high Prieſts, Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, Phariſees and other deadlie enimies, nor the moſt vvicked treaſon of Iudas, nor the extreme ingratitude of the Iewes his owne people, nor the raging furie of moſt bloudie executioners, nor anie other malice could anievvhit diminiſh, but in deede contrariwiſe infinitly increaſed the ſame. For how much further ſhe ſeeth ſinners runne in vvickednes to their euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ruine, ſo much the more ſhe thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth after their repentance and ſaluation. And therfore ſeeing her owne death ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth not to redeme mankind (for vvhom ſhe is moſt vvilling to yeld her life) ſhe ſpareth not her owne ſonne (as our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Father ſpareth him not, nor he him ſelf) but moſt freely offereth him to ſuffer al that the exact iuſtice of God requireth for the redemption of the vvhole vvorld.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:21013:56"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our Lord praying in the garden, his B. mother alſo praying at home ſeeth in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite (and after heareth by his diſciples diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed) that her ſonne is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and brought bond to Annas, and to Caiphas.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She ſeeth alſo in ſpirite (and in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heareth) that he is falſly accuſed, vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and moſt cruelly handled, beaten, moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſpit vpon, and by the Iewiſh councel iudged guiltie of death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>In the morning ſhe vnderſtandeth, that he is deliuered vnto Pilate, by him ſent to Herod, there derided and ſent back; Then moſt cruelly whipped: Crowned with thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and condemned to the Croſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Then going forth (with S. Iohn and others) ſhe meeteth her ſonne al embrued with his owne bloud, crowned with thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and carying his owne Croſſe vpon his ſore ſhoulders.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She ſeeth her ſweete ſonne fal downe vnder his Croſſe. Which then an other is compelled to carie, leſt he ſhould die in the way before he be crucified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:21013:56"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She ſeeth her ſonne, and Lord (being nailed through both ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and both fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> to the Croſſe) hoiſſed vp on height, and from thence his moſt ſacred bloud ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe euen to the ground.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Then ſhe heareth him mekely <hi>pray</hi> for thoſe that do blaſpheme and cruciſie him: Alſo <hi>promiſe paradiſe</hi> to the penitent theefe: And <hi>commend her ſelfe and his beloued diſciple, ech to other.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Againe ſhe heareth him complaine, that <hi>he is deſtitute of al temporal comforth: op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>ſſed vvith thirſt: affirme that al is conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ate: and commend his ſpirite into the handes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> his Father.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>An other great wound ſhe ſeeth made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n her ſonnes ſide with à lance, from whence iſſueth his laſt bloud, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er withal. Neither doth ſhe yet depart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>om the Croſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She taketh the dead bodie into her ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es. Which when ſhe hath à litle behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en, and waſhed with teares, it is taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>om her againe, buried, ſhut vp, and guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed that none may take it away.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:21013:57"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Conſeruat omnia verba haec conferens in corde ſuo.</head>
                        <figDesc>the risen Christ visits Mary in her chamber</figDesc>
                        <head>6. PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:21013:57"/>
                  <head>The actes of our Ladie from Chriſts Reſurrection to her ovvne death and Aſſumption.</head>
                  <p>THE vvonderful Myſterie of Chriſts moſt ſacred Paſſion being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed; ſome buſie in this ſorte, ſome in that ſorte, as they vvere very diuerſly affected; and almoſt al either doubting, or altogether deſpairing of our Lords Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; onlie the moſt faithful virgin mother firmely beleeueth, and aſſuredly expecteth her Sonnes Reſurrection the third day. Wherupon ſhe retyring to her chamber, after that ſhe hath awhile medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated vpon the ſacred vvoundes of her deare ſonne and Lord, and other torments by him ſuffered, ſhe turneth her cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s from that tragical act, to thinke vvhat he now doth vvhere he is. And ſo as vvel in the ſepulche ſhe adoreth him as God, knowing that his humaine fleſh, albeit vvithout ſoul, yet is continually vnited to his Godhead, by vvhich it vvas aſſumpted: as alſo in Limbo, vvhere his ſoule by his excellent brightnes driuing away the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted darknes, triumpheth ouer death, loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the captiuitie of the old fathers, and by his moſt glorious preſence maketh that place, vvhich hitherto vvas à priſon, to be to them as heauen or paradiſe.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:21013:58"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The third day, our Lord riſing from death appeareth firſt of al to his deare mother: who being neereſt vnto him, both by nature and grace, beſt deſerued that priuilege.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She often enioyeth his conuerſation til his Aſcenſion; and then of al others is alſo moſt ioyful for his exaltation; moſt aſſuredly beleeuing and hoping in him and aboue al deſiring his glorie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>On Whitſunday al the faithful are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with the Holie Ghoſt, but ſhe moſt abundantly; who by howe much ſhe was more ful of grace before, is ſo much more capable of increaſe therof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The reſt of her life being moſt free from al worldly cares, and altogether attending to Gods ſeruice, ſhe paſſeth with the deuouteſt Chriſtians.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time drew nere that ſhe ſhould go to her ſonne, he firſt voutchſafeth her the ſight of al his Apoſtles then liuing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept S. Thomas, who by ſpecial prouidence cometh after her death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:21013:58"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Apoſtles, and other Apoſtolical perſons, attending about her, and Angels ſinging praiſes of God, and of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhe moſt ſweetly yeldeth her ghoſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Apoſtles lay the holie bodie with al ſolemitie, in an honorable tumbe in Gethſemani. Where quires of Angels do ſing three dayes together.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>After three dayes, the Angels ceaſe ſinging, and Thomas the Apoſtle co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, who requeſteth moſt inſtantly his felow Apoſtles, that he may ſee and reuerence the ſacred bodie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>They willing to do him this fauour open the tumbe, but find nothing, ſaue only the linnen, wherin the bodie had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ene wrapped, and thoſe yelding à moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>weete ſauour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Wherby theſe ſo notable eye witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es do vndoubtedly iudge, that our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ord, who tooke fleſh of this bodie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ath raiſed, and alreadie glorified, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſumpted the ſame into heauen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:21013:59"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Eta ergo ADVOCATA nostra, illos tuos misericordes oculos ad nos conuerte.</head>
                        <figDesc>Mary seated in glory in heaven</figDesc>
                        <head>PATER NOSTER.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:21013:59"/>
                  <head>The Coronation of the glorious virgin the mother of God.</head>
                  <p>SEeing the glorie of euerie Sainct in heauen is ſo great, as no tongue can expreſſe, nor the mind of man vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>(for neither eye hath ſeene, nor care hath beard, neither hath it aſcended into the hart of man, vvhat things God hath prepared for them that loue him)</hi> how much leſſe can the glorie of the mother of God (exalted aboue al the quires of Angels) be vttered or conceiued by anie mortal man? But ſhal we therfore be ſilent and ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at al therof? ſhal we alſo ceaſe to thinke and meditate therof, becauſe it ſo farre ſurmounteth both our ſenſe and vnderſtanding? No, in no wiſe can we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſo excuſed; but ſo much the more we are bound to reioice, and as we can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſeing we can not as we would) vtter forth the praiſes of the mother of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, mother of grace, mother of life, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of glorie, mother of God, now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eigning Quene of heauen, whom alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <hi>(of the faithful in earth)</hi> do cal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leſſed, deuoutly ſerue, religiouſly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, euery where preach, magnifie; and humbly beſeke to obtaine for vs al things behooful for our ſaluation.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:21013:60"/>
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Quene of al holie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, widowes, and Virgins; And of the Orders of Angels, Archangels, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Quene of al holie Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſons, Paſtors, and Biſhops; And of the Angelical Poteſtates, Powers, and Dommations.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>She is crowned Quene of al holie Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes, Prophets, Martyrs and Apoſtles; And of the Thrones, Cherubims, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphims: And of al created perſons.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="creed">
                     <head>Credo in Deum.</head>
                     <p>BE thankful therfore (ô my ſoul) to the moſt bleſſed Trinitie, who for thee and for al mankind, hath not only ſent the Sonne of God IESVS CHRIST, à new and heauenlie Adam, to redeme the world from the thraldome into which we fel through the old tereſtrial Adam: but alſo vvheras our old mother Eue was in à ſort, the cauſe or occaſion of our ruine, (by ſuggeſting to Adam that ſinne, which was our vniuerſal deſtruction) hath beſtowed vpon vs à new and moſt bleſſed woman, the immaculate virgin MARIE, who in like ſort, is à meanes of our ſaluation,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:21013:60"/> by cooperating with our Sauiour, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Myſteries of our Redemption, and by continual interceſſion for vs to her Sonne, much more profiting vs, by ech of theſe waies, then the other woman did vs harme. And to thee (o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt ſacred virgin) what thankes ſhal I render, for thy exceding great benignitie and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes towards me, and the whole world? Or with what praiſes ſhal I (a poore wrech) extol thee? whoſe incomparable excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie (as à ſhadowe may reſemble à bodie, or à figure ſignifie à truth) was long before thy birth, repreſented by the brightnes of the ſea ſtarre; by the bewtie of the moone; the clearnes of the ſune; the buſh burning and not conſuming; Aarons rodde; Gedeons wool-fleece; the looking glaſſe without blemiſh, the fountaine of the gardens; the welſpting of liuing water; the garden iuuironed; the lilie of the valley; the palme tree in Cades; the roſe in Ierico; the bewtiful Oliue; the high Cedar in Libanus; the Cipreſſe tree in Sion; the towre of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid; the throne of Salomon; the citie of God; the gate of heauen, and by manie the like: And by al the renowmed women from the beginning of the world; but by none of al theſe, no nor by al together, can be ſufficiently expreſſed thy ſingular graces, giftes, vertues, priuilegies, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:21013:61"/> dignities, who art al faire, neuer touched with anie ſpot. who alwaies remaining a virgin, haſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued him in thy wom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, whom the heauens could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend. Who art the ſingular ſpouſe of the Father of heauen, the mother of the Sonne of God, and aboue al mere creatures, ful of the Holie Ghoſt, the inaeſtimable gemme of the celeſtial and terreſtrial world. which we thy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like clients, euery where moſt aſſuredly beleeuing, and ſincerly profeſſing, do admire thy ſingular grace, and congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late thy moſt praeemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t glorie. To thee we repaire, crauing in al our neceſſities thy praerogatiue interceſſion, becauſe next to thy ſonne, thou art our aduoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, our hope, our refuge, our comforth, our helpe, our ſupreme Ladie and Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, mother of al good, mother of Chriſt, mother of God. we therfore moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſech thy celeſtial Maieſtie, vout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to intreate thy ſonne for vs ſinners, nowe and in the houre of our death, that we may be made worthie of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, through the ſame Chriſt our Lord thy Sonne, who with the Father and Holie Ghoſt liueth and reigneth one God world without end. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="corone__rosary">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:21013:61"/>
               <head>The Corone of our Lord. With particular pointes to be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated, in ſaying the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In nomine Patris &amp; Filij <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> &amp; Spiritus Sancti. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the risen Christ</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE B. Trinitie decreed before al worlds, that the Sonne of God ſhould be borne of à virgin, by death on the croſſe redeme mankind, and iudge the whole world.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:21013:62"/>
                  <head>The coming of our Sauiour into this world.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <head>1. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Archangel Gabriel ſent from God ſaluteth the B. virgin MARIE, and imparteth to her, that ſhe ſhal conceiue the Sonne of God. wherunto ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, CHRIST IS INCARNAT, God made man.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The B. virgin viſiting her coſin Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, the Infant in Elizabeths wom be is ſanctified, and leapeth for ioy of our Sauiours preſence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our SAVIOVR is borne in Bethleem, wrapped in clothes and laid in à ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. Angels declare his birth to poore ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hards, and ſing: <hi>Glorie to God in the hiegheſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The ſhephards preſently do viſite this childe in Bethleem: and finding al as the Angel had told them, they returne glorifying God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The eight day folowing the childe is circumciſed, and his name called IESVS, that is, SAAIOVR. <hi>for he ſhal ſaue his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their ſinnes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:21013:62"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Three Sages, called Gaſpar Melchior and Baltaſar, coming from the Eaſt adore him: ech one fotering three giftes, gold frankincenſe and myrrh.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our Lord is preſented in the Temple. His mother offereth a paire of turtles, and two pigeons. Simeon ioyfully taketh the childe into his armes. He and holie Anne do prophecie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Herod ſeeking to kil our Sauiour in his cradle, Ioſeph warned by an Angel flieth with the childe and his mother into Aegypt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Herod killeth al the male-children, vnder two yeres old, in and nere Bethlee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They are al Martyrs. And the Diuels flie out of the Idols in Aegypt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Herod being dead Ioſeph with the child and his mother returne from Aegypt, and dwel in Nazareth of Galilee, not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to go into Iurie, for feare of Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus Herods ſonne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <head>1. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The virgin mother cooperateth with the B. Trinitie, and our Sauiour, in al theſe Myſteries; meditating vpon the ſame.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:21013:63"/>
                  <head>Our Sauiours conuerſation in this world.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <head>1. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our Lord at the age of twelue yeares, remaining in Ieruſalem, vnknowne to his parents, after three dayes is found in the Temple ſitting amongſt the Doctors.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>His mother demanding why he ſtayed behind them, he anſwereth, that he muſt be occupied in his Fathers affayres. And ſo returning to Nazareth, liueth ſubiect to them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. Pater noſter.</head>
                     <p>In the thirtith yeare of his age, he is baptiſed by Iohn Baptiſt. The Holie Ghoſt deſcending vpon him, à voice declareth: This is my Sonne, in whom I am wel pleaſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>In the deſert, he faſteth fourtie dayes and fourtie nights, is tempted and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſheth the Diuel: Inſtructing vs, as wel by example as by word, how to fight with the ſpiritual enimie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Then he calleth diſciples, preacheth the kingdom of heauen to be at hand, and to be obtayned paenance, and by perfect workes of iuſtice.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:21013:63"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He confirmeth his doctrine by miracles, Scriptures, reaſons, teſtimonie of good men, and by his owne ſo perfect life, that none can charge him with anie ſinne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He often foretelleth, that he ſhal be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed in Ieruſalem, deliuered to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, mocked, whipped, ſpitt vpon, cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and the third day ſhal riſe againe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>That none be ſcandalized with his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he fortelleth of the glorie to come; And before three of his Apoſtles is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured, ſhewing them à glimſe of his glorie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He often detecteth the calumniations, of his enimies, conuinceth their errors, reproueth their ſinnes, and ſometimes deliuereth him ſelfe miraculouſly out of their handes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He rideth into Ieruſalem, is receiued with great triumph, and ſaluted king of Iſrael. And driueth byers and ſellers out of the Temple.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The B. virgin is partaker with her ſonne in ioy and tribularion; moſt diligently heareth his diuine worde, and of al others moſt faithfully keepeth the ſame.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:21013:64"/>
                  <head>Our Sauiours paſſing forth of this world.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <head>1. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our Sauiour eateth the Paſchal lambe with his tvvelue Apoſtles, waſheth their feete, and inſtituteth the B Sacrament and Sacrifice of his owne bodie and bloud.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He praieth in the garden, that the cuppe of his Paſſion may be taken from him; yet ſubmitteth his wil to his Fathers wil, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth bloud, is comforted by an Angel, and betrayed by Iudas.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>He is brought bound to Annas, and Caiphas; ſcornfully and cruelly handled, falſly accuſed, thriſe denied by Peter, and condemned by the Iewes councel as guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="prayer">
                     <head>4. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>In the morning he is deliuered to Pilate, by him found innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; yet ſent to Herod, by him alſo iudged innocent, but mocked as à foole, and ſent back to P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>late.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="prayer">
                     <head>5. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Iewes with great clamour require, that Barabbas be deliuered, and IESVS crucified. Pilate to appeaſe their furie, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth our B. Sauiour to be moſt cruelly whipped. <hi>vvhere he receiueth 5490. ſtripes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="prayer">
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:21013:64"/>
                     <head>6. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>They put on him a ſcarlet robe, a crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of thornes, and à reede in his hand, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting him as King. Pilate ſo ſheweth him ſaying: ECCE HOMO. the Iewes crie, Crucifie him, Crucifie him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="prayer">
                     <head>7. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Pilate waſheth his handes, proteſting that he is innocent; the people crie, his bloud be vpon vs, and vpon our children, &amp; Pilate fearing to offend Caeſar iudgeth Chriſt to be crucified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="prayer">
                     <head>8. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Taking away the ſcarlet robe, but lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the crowne on his head, they cauſe him to carie his owne croſſe; he falleth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det it, but leſt he die in the way, they force an other to carie it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="prayer">
                     <head>9. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Our Sauiour crucified betwen two thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, deſtitute of al temporal comforth, in extreme paine ſheweth exceding patience, and infinite charitie towards al, frends and foes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="prayer">
                     <head>10. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>After three houres (al things being now conſummate) he yeldeth the ghoſt. His ſoule preſently triumpheth in limbo: in the euening his bodie is honorably buried</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>His conſtant mother aboue al others ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vvith him: the ſvvord of ſorovv often pearcing her hart and afflicting her vvith the paines of death.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:21013:65"/>
                  <head>The glorie of our Lord after his Paſſion.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="prayer">
                     <head>1. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The third day our Lord riſeth glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly from death, deliuering out of limbo al the Sainctes of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; appeareth firſt to his mother, then to others: diſpoſeth manie things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning to the kingdome of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="prayer">
                     <head>2. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The fourtith day he aſcendeth into heauen, ſitteth on the right hand of his Father, our ſingular and proper Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, by whom we haue manie inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediators, and interceſſors.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="prayer">
                     <head>3. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Vpon Whitſunday he ſendeth the Holie Ghoſt in viſible ſignes: By whom he gathereth, gouerneth, ſanctifieth, conſerueth, and glorifieth his Church continually to the end of the world.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="creed">
                     <head>Credo in Deum.</head>
                     <p>OVR Lord IESVS CHRIST, who before al worlds was ordained to be the Redeemer of mankind: Who at the time appointed was borne of the virgin MARIE, in great humilitie and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:21013:65"/> pouertie: who ſuſtayned moſt great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, calling al men to penance, inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting al by example and word to grace, deſirous to ſaue al: who after infinite traualies, reproches and torments, at laſt ſuffered the moſt ignominious, and moſt bitter death vpon the Croſſe: who finally is gloriouſly riſen from death, aſcended into heauen, from thence ſent the Holie Ghoſt: who continually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth, and ſanctifieth his Church in earth: The ſelfe ſame Lord and Redemer wil come againe in great powre, and Maieſtie, Iudge of al, Angels and men: And wil render to euerie one (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they ſhal deſerue wel or euil) euerlaſting paine, or euerlaſting glorie AMEN.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="rosary">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:21013:66"/>
               <head>A briefe Roſarie of fiftene Pater noſters and Aues with one Crede: in memorie of eight ioyes and ſeuen ſorovves of the moſt B. Virgin MARIE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In nomine Patris &amp; Filij <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> &amp; Spiritus Sancti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed be the moſt holie, and indiuiſible Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, novve and euer vvorld vvithout end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="prayer">
                  <head>1. <hi>Pater. Aue. The firſt ioy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Annunciation and Conception of Chriſt, wherby God is made man, and the B. virgin the mother of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="prayer">
                  <head>2. <hi>Pater. Aue. The ſecond ioy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The B. Virgin viſiting S. Elizabeth, the infant in Elizabeths wombe, both the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Zacharias, their kins folke, and neighbours do al reioyce.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="prayer">
                  <head>3. <hi>Pater. Aue. The third ioy</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Our Sauiour is borne, the Angels ſing the ſhepheards viſite the Infant, the Sages adore him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="prayer">
                  <head>4. <hi>Pater. Aue. The fourth ioy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Preſenting her ſonne in the Temple, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon ioyfully taketh the childe into his armes: he and holie Anne do prophecie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="prayer">
                  <head>5. <hi>Pater. Aue. The firſt ſorowe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Ioſeph vvith the childe and his mother flie into Aegypt, parting avvay by night.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="prayer">
                  <head>6. <hi>Pater. Aue. The ſecond ſorowe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Our Sauiour being tvvelue yeres old, is loſt three dayes, his parents ſeking him vvith great griefe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:21013:66"/>
                  <head>7. <hi>Pater. Aue. The third ſorowe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In the thirtith yere of his age, our Lord taketh leaue of his mother, as no longer to dvvel in her familie, Ioſeph alſo dieth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="prayer">
                  <head>8. <hi>Pater. Aue. The fourth ſorowe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The B. Virgin heareth that her ſonne is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; cruelly handled, vvhipped, crovvned with thornes, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned to be crucified.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="prayer">
                  <head>9. <hi>Pater. Aue. The fith ſorowe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The afflicted mother meteth her ſonne carying his Croſſe, and ſeeth him fal dovvne vnder it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="prayer">
                  <head>10. <hi>Pater. Aue. The ſixt ſorowe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>She ſeeth her ſonne crucified betvven tvvo theeues, and after extreme paines, to yeld the ghoſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="prayer">
                  <head>11. <hi>Pater. Aue. The ſeuenth ſorowe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>She taketh his bodie in her armes, And it is taken from her againe and buried.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="prayer">
                  <head>12. <hi>Pater. Aue. The fifth ioy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Our Sauiour riſing from death, firſt of al appeareth to his deare mother.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="prayer">
                  <head>13. <hi>Pater. Aue. The ſixt ioy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The bleſſed mother reioyceth aboue al others, for her ſonnes Aſcenſion, and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in heauen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="prayer">
                  <head>14. <hi>Pater. Aue. The ſeuenth ioy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>She alſo reioyceth moſt for the coming of the Holie Ghoſt, and is thervvith moſt abundantly replemſhed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="prayer">
                  <head>15. <hi>Pater. Aue. The eight ioy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The glorious mother of God, is both in ſoul and bodie aſſumpted into heauen, and exalted aboue al the orders of Angels.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="creed">
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:21013:67"/>
                  <p>OVR Lord IESVS CHRIST, in whom there could neuer be anie ſinne, And the moſt bleſſed virgin his mother, being alwayes preſerued from al ſpot or blemiſh therof, ſuffered ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme paines; and ſo entred in to their glorie, leauing vnto vs example to folow their ſteppes. How much more then are we (moſt miſerable creatures, being loadden with ſinnes, compaſſed about with infirmities, and ſubiect to al dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous tentations) bound to ſuſtaine ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie chaſtiſments, and ſweete corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, reioycing in hope, patient in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribulation, inſtant in prayer, not to be wearied in our mindes, nor faint vnder the rodde of our heauenly Fathers diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, that we may at laſt reigne with them, be glorified with them, and made heyres of God, felowe heyres of Chriſt our Sauiour, and our moſt bleſſed Ladie his mother, of aeternal ioy and glorie, which no man can take away from vs. Which he graunt vnto vs, who with his owne bloud purchaſed the ſame for vs, by the interceſſion of his moſt ſweete mother, and of al his glorious Saincts. AMEN.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="litany">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:21013:67"/>
               <head>LITANIES GATHERED OVT OF THE CORONE OF OVR LORD.</head>
               <div type="versicle_and_response">
                  <p>KYrie eleyſon. Chriſte eleyſon. Kyrie eleyſon. Chriſte audi nos. Chiſte exaudi nos.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Ab Angelo Gabriele an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciate, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 Baptiſtam tuum in vtero ſanctificans, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>3 Ex virgine nate, &amp; ab An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis agnite, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>4 A Paſtoribus in praeſepio viſitate, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>5 Circunciſe, &amp; nomine IESV appellate, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>6 A Magis (Gentium primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs) adorate, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>7 Preſentate, &amp; in Simeonis vlnas ſuſcepte, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>8 In Aegypto cum parenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus exulans, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>9 Simulachra Aegyptiorum deſtruens, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>10 Archelaum fugiens, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth inhabitans. CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:21013:68"/>
                  <p>Virgo benedicta his omnibus cooperata, or a pro nobis.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Triduo amiſſe, &amp; inter Doctores inuente, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 In Patris negotijs ſemper occupate, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>3 A Ioanne in Iordane bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zate, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>4 In deſer to ieiunans, &amp; ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatorem vincens, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>5 Exemplo &amp; verbo legem Dei docens, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>6 Miraculorum &amp; ſermon is virtute potens, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>7 De Paſſione tua, &amp; Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectione praemonens, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>8 In monte coram Apoſtolis tranſfigurate, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>9 Ab inimicorum fraude &amp; furore te liberans, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>10 Ieroſolymam cum trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho ingrediens, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Virgo ſacratiſſima actionum Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lij tui particeps, ora pro nobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Sacramentorum &amp; Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij Inſtitutor, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 Patris voluntati tuam ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittens, &amp; ſanguinem ſudans. CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:21013:68"/>
                     <item>3 A concilio Iudeorum fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſò condemnate, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>4 Pilato tradite, &amp; ab He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode irriſe, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>5 Barabbe poſtpoſite, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſime flagellate, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>6 Spinis coronate, coccino indute, &amp; illuſe, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>7 Pilati ſententia ad morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Crucis damnate, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>8 Crucem tuam baiulans, &amp; ſub illa corruens, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>9 Cruci affixe, &amp; omni ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio deſtitute, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>10 Sponte tua pro vita mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di moriens, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Virgo afflictiſsima, plus omnibus Filio tuo compaſſa, ora pro nobis</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Tertia die a morte glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſe reſurgens, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 In coelum Aſcendens, &amp; ad dextera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Patris ſede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>3 Spiritu Sancto de caelis miſſo Eccleſiam tuam regens, CHRISTE Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Virgo glorioſa anima &amp; corpore in coelos aſſump ta, or a pro nobis.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>℣. Oportuit pati Chriſtum.</item>
                     <item>℟. Et ita intrare in gloriam ſuam.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:21013:69"/>
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>CHriſte omnipotens, qui ab aeterno Filius Dei exiſtens, humanum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in tempore Naſcendo laetificaſti; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiendo &amp; Moriendo a peccati captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate redemiſti; Reſurgendo ab inferis liberaſti; Aſcendendo in caelos adduxiſti; praeſta quaeſumus: vt qui ſummis hiſce beneficijs laeti gaudemus; venientem quoque te Iudicem ſecuri videamus, &amp; glorioſum Remuneratorem habeamus. Qui viuis &amp; regnas, cum Deo Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, in vnitate Spiritus Sancti Deus. Per omnia ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula ſaeculorum.</p>
                  <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="litany">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:21013:69"/>
               <head>LITANIES GATHERED OVT OF THE CORONE OF OVR LADIE.</head>
               <div type="call_and_response">
                  <head>KYrie eleyſon. Chriſte eleyſon. Kyrie eleyſon. Pater de caelis Deus, tua te orante prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>electa virgine, Miſerere nobis.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Ad ſerpentem conterendum foemina promiſſa, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 Mater viuentium in Eua no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>3 Per faeminas ſupra naturam fertiles figurata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>4 Per res multas mirabiles prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>5 Per omnes clariſſimas mulie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res praenotata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>6 Oraculis Propheticis praenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>7 Singularis Dei Sponſa à Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomone deſcripta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>8 A Sybillis (diuino ſpiritu af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flatis) decantata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>9 Ioachimo &amp; Annae diuinitùs data filia, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>10 Singulari priuilegio à pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis praeſeruata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:21013:70"/>
                  <p>Fili Redemptor mundi Deus, tua te orante pia Matre virgine, Miſerere nobis.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Virgo virginum MARIA dicta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 Gratiam vt nunquam pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res conſecuta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>3 Triennis in templo praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>4 Diuinis &amp; pijs operibus ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per intenta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>5 Virtutibus omnibus pleniſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè exornata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>6 Religioſae virginitatis cultrix prima, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>7 Perfectum vitae ſtatum plenè adepta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>8 Filij Deiex virgine naſcituri praeſcia, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>9 Futurae Dei Matri ancillandi ſtudioſa, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>10 Ioſepho nupta, virgo ſemper permanſura, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Spiritus, Sancte Deus, tua te ornate ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulari ſponſa, Miſerere nobis.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Ab Angelo ſalutata gratia plena, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 Quod Deum conciperes ab Angelo edocta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:21013:70"/>
                     <item>3 In Matrem electa ancilla Dei profeſſa, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>4 Dato conſenſu ſtatim Mater Dei facta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>5 In cuius voce exultat in vtero Baptiſa, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>6 De tua prole, anxio viro, tu quoque anxia, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>7 De Chriſto nato gaudens Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alma, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>8 De IESV circunciſo Mater afflicta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>9 Adorantibus Filium Magis Mater laeta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>10 Filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſentans de doloribus praemonita, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Sancta Trinitas vnus Deus tua te oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te excellentiſſima perſona creata, Miſerere nobis.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Poſt exilium in Aegypto Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilaeae incola, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 De Filio amiſſo Mater dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſa, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>3 De illo inuento Mater conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>4 Simul exiſtens Mater, Virgo, Vidua, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>5 Aquam in vinum vertendi Filio cauſa, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:21013:71"/>
                     <item>6 Factorum &amp; verborum Filij obſeruantiſſima, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>7 Propter inſigniſſimum Filium Mater laudata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>8 Quia Deum audiſti, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quia genuiſti, magis beata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>9 In aduerſis &amp; ſecundis aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliſſima, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>10 Filio Rege ſalutato, Paſſioni attenta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, tua te oxante Matre tecum in Cruce patiente, Miſerere nobis.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Ob Filium inimicis traditum Mater maeſtiſſima, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 Ob Filium viliſſimè tractatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mater triſtiſſima. Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>3 Ob Filium flagellatum, &amp; ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis coronatum, Mater af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictiſſima, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>4 Filio crucem portanti pia Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obuia, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>5 Filium ſub Cruce corruente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mater contemplata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>6 Filio crucifixo, Mater corde transfixa, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>7 Mater per Filium diſcipulo commendata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:21013:71"/>
                     <item>8 Mater, moriente Filio, dolores mortis paſſa, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>9 Mater Filij latus videns ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riri lancea, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>10 Mater exangue Filij corpus in vlnas amplexa, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, tua te orante Matre glorioſa, Miſerere nobis,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 A Reſurgente Filio Mater prima viſitata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 Aſcendente Filio plus omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus gauiſa, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>3 Spiritus Sancti gratia ſuper omnes repletiſſima, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>4 Mundi curis libera diuinis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiſſima, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>5 Apoſtoloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concurſu moriens honorata, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>6 Super omnes Angelos ſcande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Filio proxima, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>7 Sepulta Gethſemani coeleſti cum Pſalmodia, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>8 Vt Thomas veneretur, in tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulo quaeſita, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>9 Apoſtolis quaerentibus nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi inuenta, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>10 Corporis quoque gloria in coelis potita, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:21013:72"/>
                  <p>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, ipſa te orante caelorum Regina, Miſerere nobis.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Angelorum Archangelorum, &amp; Principatuum Regina, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>2 Poteſtatum, Virtutum, &amp; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minationum Regina, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>3 Thronoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Cherubim &amp; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphim omnium<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Regina, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>℣. In omni tribulatione &amp; anguſtia noſtra:</item>
                     <item>℟. Succurrat nobis pijſſima Virgo Maria.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>INterueniat pro nobis quaeſumus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine IESV Chriſte, nunc &amp; in hora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mortis noſtrae apud tuam clementiam B. Virgo Maria Mater tua, Domina no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, cuius ſacratiſſimam animam, in tua Paſſione, doloris gladius pertranſiuit. Et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu ô Domina noſtra, coelorum Regina &amp; Imperatrix glorioſisſima, in tuam be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictam fidem atque ſingularem tute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, &amp; in ſinum miſericordiae tuae nos<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuſcipe. Tibi hodie, &amp; quotidie, &amp; in hora exitus noſtri, animas noſtras, cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pora noſtra, fortunas noſtras, totam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:21013:72"/> noſtram &amp; vitae finem commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: vt per tuam ſanctiſsimam interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem, &amp; per tua merita, omnia noſtra dirigantur &amp; diſponantur, cogitationes, verba, &amp; opera, ſecundum tuam, tuique Filij voluntatem. Per eundem Dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtrum IESVM Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Filium tuum: Qui cum Patre, &amp; Spiritu Sancto viuit &amp; regnat Deus, in ſaecula ſaeculorum.</p>
               </div>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="litany">
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The doleful ſtate of our B. Ladie, vnder the Croſſe of her Sonne.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>STabat mater doloroſa,</l>
                     <l>Iuxta Crucem lachrymoſa,</l>
                     <l>Dum pendebat Filius.</l>
                     <l>Cuius animam gementem</l>
                     <l>Contriſtantem &amp; dolentem,</l>
                     <l>Pertranſiuit gladius.</l>
                     <l>O quam triſtis &amp; afflicta,</l>
                     <l>Fuit illa benedicta</l>
                     <l>Mater vnigeniti!</l>
                     <l>Quae maerebat &amp; dolebat</l>
                     <l>Et tremebat, cum videbat,</l>
                     <l>Nati poenas inclyti.</l>
                     <l>Quis eſt homo qui non fleret,</l>
                     <l>Chriſti Matrem ſi videret,</l>
                     <l>In tanto ſupplicio?</l>
                     <pb n="226" facs="tcp:21013:73"/>
                     <l>Quis non poſſet contriſtari,</l>
                     <l>Piam Matrem contemplari,</l>
                     <l>Dolentem cum Filio!</l>
                     <l>Pro peccatis ſuae gentis,</l>
                     <l>Vidit IESVM in tormentis,</l>
                     <l>Et flagellis ſubditum.</l>
                     <l>Vidit ſuum dulcem natum</l>
                     <l>Morientem, deſolatum,</l>
                     <l>Dum emiſit ſpiritum.</l>
                     <l>Eia Mater fons amoris,</l>
                     <l>Me ſentire vim doloris</l>
                     <l>Fac, vt tecum lugeam.</l>
                     <l>Fac vt ardeat cor meum</l>
                     <l>In amando Chriſtum Deum,</l>
                     <l>Vt ſibi complaceam.</l>
                     <l>Sancta mater iſtud agas,</l>
                     <l>Crucifixi fige plagas</l>
                     <l>Cordi meo valide.</l>
                     <l>Tui Nati vulnerati,</l>
                     <l>Tam dignati pro me pati,</l>
                     <l>Poenas mecum diuide.</l>
                     <l>Fac me vere tecum flere,</l>
                     <l>Crucifixo condolere,</l>
                     <l>Donec ego vixero.</l>
                     <l>Iuxta Crucem tecum ſtare,</l>
                     <l>Te libenter ſociare</l>
                     <l>In planctu deſidero.</l>
                     <l>Virgo virginum plaeclara,</l>
                     <l>Mihi iam non ſis amara,</l>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:21013:73"/>
                     <l>Fac me tecum plangere.</l>
                     <l>Fac vt portem Chriſti mortem,</l>
                     <l>Paſſionis eius ſortem,</l>
                     <l>Et plagas recolere.</l>
                     <l>Fac me plagis vulnerari,</l>
                     <l>Cruce hac inebriari,</l>
                     <l>Ob amorem Filij.</l>
                     <l>Inflammatus &amp; accenſus,</l>
                     <l>Per te virgo ſim defenſus,</l>
                     <l>In die Iudicij.</l>
                     <l>Fac me Cruce cuſtodiri,</l>
                     <l>Morte Chriſti praemuniri,</l>
                     <l>Confoueri gratia.</l>
                     <l>Quando corpus morietur,</l>
                     <l>Fac vt animae donetur</l>
                     <l>Paradiſi gloria. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="call_and_response">
                  <list>
                     <item>℣. Tuam ipſius animam pertranſiuit gladius.</item>
                     <item>℟. Vt reuelentur ex multis cordibus cogitationes.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>INterueniat pro nobis queſumus Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne IESV Chriſte, nunc &amp; in hora mortis noſtre, apud tuam clementiam beata virgo Maria mater tua, cuius ſacratiſſimam ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam in hora tue Paſſionis, doloris gladius pettranfiuit: per te IESV Chriſte Saluator mundi: Qui cum Patre &amp; Spiritu Sancto viuis &amp; regnas in ſaecula ſaeculorum.</p>
                  <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:21013:74"/>
            <head>THE APPROBATION.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Libellum himc, à viro Anglo, docto &amp; pio perlegendum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rauimus; eiuſque iudicio probatum, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum duximus. 25. Ianuarij.</hi> 1599.</p>
            <p>Matthias Archiepu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Mechlinienſis.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21013:74"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
